<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaracion of the state, wherin all heretikes dooe leade their liues and also of their continuall indeuer, and propre fruictes, which beginneth in the. 38. chapiter, and so to thende of the woorke. By Iohn Gwynnethe clerke.</title>
            <title>Confutacyon of the fyrst parte of Frythes boke</title>
            <author>Gwynneth, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 284:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaracion of the state, wherin all heretikes dooe leade their liues and also of their continuall indeuer, and propre fruictes, which beginneth in the. 38. chapiter, and so to thende of the woorke. By Iohn Gwynnethe clerke.</title>
                  <title>Confutacyon of the fyrst parte of Frythes boke</title>
                  <author>Gwynneth, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12, [1], 13-51 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[In Fletestrete in the hous of Thomas Berthelet],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1554.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Frith, John.  A boke made by John Frith prisoner in the tower of London.</note>
                  <note>A dialogue.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>A revised and enlarged edition of: The confutacyon of the fyrst parte of Frythes boke.</note>
                  <note>The leaf between 12 and 13 is numbered 6.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A declaration of an heretike.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frith, John, 1503-1533. --  Boke made by John Frith prisoner in the tower of London.</term>
               <term>Heretics, Christian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3752:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3752:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARACION of the ſtate, wherin all heretikes dooe leade their liues: And alſo of their continuall indeuer, and propre fruictes, which beginneth in the .38. chapiter, and ſo to thende of the woorke</p>
            <p>By Iohn Gwynnethe clerke.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouer. 16.</bibl>
               <p>Eſt via, quae videtur homini recta, et nouiſſima eius ducunt ad mortem.</p>
            </q>
            <p>There is a waie, whiche ſemeth to a man ſtreight, and yet the endes therof leaden to perdicion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDINI.</hi> 1554.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3752:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3752:2"/>
            <head>To the readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E'L diſpoſed and good chriſten rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſo it is, that about. xvii. or xviii. yeres paſt, I beganne to write ageinſt Frithes booke which he made ageinſt the veritee of the holy ſacrament of the Altare: And I beeing then, where a print was in vſe and occupacion, procuryng the ſame for the puttinge foorthe of that I did intende, by that tyme ii. or iii. chapiters of that I had written was printed for aſſaie, to ſee how the printer wolde and coulde ſet it forth, I fell ſo ſicke, that I was fayne to gette me to London, for the remedy and helpe of mine infirmitee, where I laie a longe tyme in greate daunger. And before I was able to go abrode, the printer (as I ſuppoſe for lacke of worke) beeing where he myght come by my ſcrowes and papers, printed vp the reſte of that I had doone, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuche ſorte, as he coulde pike it out of my firſt draught therof. And ſent me the booke, before I was able (as I ſayd) to come out of my chamber: wherin, he diſpleaſed me ſo muche, that I did not intende to go any farder with the matter. And that not only becauſe he did ſo muche with out my conſent, but alſo ſpecially becauſe it was doone, before I had peruſed and dewly examined that I had written, as that and other like thinges, dothe alway require. For I thinke there be no writer, that willeth any matter of weight to paſſe his handes, before he hath made with hym ſelfe, vpon the firſt drawght, a dew exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacion therof, wherby, he may perceiue and ſee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhulde nede, either any addicion, or diminucion, or
<pb facs="tcp:3752:3"/>
els alteracion, and better diſpoſicion of order, wherby the worke maie bee the more compendious, and of leſſe difficultee or tediouſnes vnto the readers. For my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was (if I might than haue had tyme) to digeſte, diſpoſe and order the matter after this ſort: Firſt, that it ſhulde appere by it ſelfe, what the ſtate of an heretike is, and in what condicion he leadeth his life. And after that, what maner of foundacion it is, where vpon Frith (as he ſaieth) doth builde and frame his purpoſe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it ſhulde appered alſo by it ſelfe, how falſely and fooliſhely he dothe take, not only the holy ſcripture, but alſo the olde holy fathers and auncient doctours of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, whom he boſteth ſo muche to make for him, not withſtandinge that thei are all directly ageinſt hym. Fourthly, what his reaſons and argumentes are, which he pretendeth to be no leſſe then inuincible, and yet ſo falſe and fooliſhe in dede, as are not worthe the heringe. Fiftly, what is to be ſayd vnto hym and all his adherentes, in that they holde, that one bodie can not bee in two places at once. Sixtly, that the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitee therof (whan they haue all doone) is yet probable, by very naturall reaſon, one principle graunted, whiche no reaſonable man can denie. This was mine order, whiche I did intende. And although I were then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apointed therof, thorowe the haſtie raſhnes of the printer (as is aforeſaid) intending therfore to go no farder with all, litle thinking then, that the venim of Frithes booke wolde haue ſpredde ſo farre abrode, as the lamentable experience therof doth preſently declare: yet now vpon that, and other ſuche vrgent occaſions, as I haue ſince and dayly do ſee, I haue returned vnto my firſt purpoſe ageyn, and ſo gone forwarde with all, that I haue newe
<pb facs="tcp:3752:3"/>
written all that I wrote before, with ſuch alteracion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as the tyme and change of thinges hath ſynce mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred great, and worthie occaſion. Wherfore moſte gentill readers, vſe therin your indifferent iudgement, and impute of my labour no more vnto me, but only a mocion or occaſion geuen vnto other, that can dooe much better. And thus I committe you to god.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The argumentes of the chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN introduction of the matter. Cap. 1.</item>
               <item>That no heretike can knowe, or ſo muche as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue or thinke, that he is an heretike. Cap. 2.</item>
               <item>The cauſe why, that an heretike can not knowe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, or thinke that he is an heretike. Cap. 3.</item>
               <item>¶ What is the cauſe that hereſie is ſo ſildome or neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. Cap. 4.</item>
               <item>That theſe wordes of the prophet (The foliſh man ſayd in his herte, There is no God, are well and trewly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande of euery heretike. Cap. 5.</item>
               <item>Whether the trewthe of all the whole feithe, be contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in euery ſingular article or no. Cap. 6.</item>
               <item>That the trewthe of the feithe is no more in the whole, than in the leaſt parte of it, nor no leſſe in the leaſt parte, than in all the whole, nor none other in any one parte of it than in any other, or in them all together. Cap. 7.</item>
               <item>That the trewthe and the thynge, wherin it is, are not bothe one. And therfore although the thynges differ, yet the trewthe in them diffreth not. Cap. 8.</item>
               <item>That trewthe is inalterable, and that all heretikes are deceiued, not only in thoſe articles, whiche thei directly denie, but alſo in thoſe, whiche thei ſeme and thynke thei graunt. Cap. 9.</item>
               <item> That ſuche difference is betwene the trewthe of one
<pb facs="tcp:3752:4"/>
article, and the trewthe of an other, as ther is betwene Iohn, the name of one man, and Iohn the name of an other. Cap. 10.</item>
               <item>That ther is but one trewthe in all and euery maner of thynge. And therfore what nede it to be ſought in ſo many thynges as it is, whan the ſekers therof haue it all redy in ſome thynge. Cap. 11.</item>
               <item>That trewthe, whiche is not diuerſe, doth diuerſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue it ſelfe in diuers thynges, and is more expedient to be had in ſome thynges than in ſome. Cap. 12.</item>
               <item>What is to bee vnderſtande of theſe wordes of chriſte, I am the waie, trewthe, and lyfe. Cap. 13.</item>
               <item>When theſe three, The waie, trewthe and life, are all but one trewth, why thei are ſo put, as thoughe thei were otherwiſe. Cap. 14.</item>
               <item>That more or leſſe of trewthe, dothe muche differ from more or leſſe than trewthe. Cap. 15.</item>
               <item>That he whiche ſeketh after trewthe, ſeketh for none other, but that he hath all redie, and yet laboureth not in vaine, nor without nede. Cap. 16.</item>
               <item>If one trewthe bee indifferent to bothe the colours of blacke and white, why maie not the blacke be trewly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led white, and the white blacke. Cap. 17.</item>
               <item>That the ſcripture dooeth ſpeake ofte tymes after the commune maner of them, to whom it ſpeaketh, and not after the proper perfection of the thynge, wherof it ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Cap. 18.</item>
               <item>That if there be but one trewthe in all and euery thyng, it ſemeth to folowe, that who ſo euer denieth the trewthe of any thynge, muſt nedes be an heretike, becauſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the ſame trewthe that an heretike dothe. Cap. 19.</item>
               <item>That trewth byndeth not like in all thynges: and how a man maie denie the ſame trewthe whiche an heretike dooeth, and yet be no heretike at all. Cap. 20.</item>
               <item>The cauſe why that the deniall of one article dooeth more hynder and leſe, than the confeſſion and graunt of all the reſte, is able to get or ſaue. Cap. 21.</item>
               <item>That who ſo euer denieth Chriſte, as the Turkes doe, to bee verie god, denieth hym alſo therin, to be a veraie
<pb facs="tcp:3752:4"/>
man. Cap. 22.</item>
               <item>Howe the propre ſignificacion of this name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and this name Chriſt, doo the differ. Cap. 23.</item>
               <item>That it differeth muche to denie a thynge to be the ſame that it is, and to denie it to be in this or that, or here or there. Cap. 24.</item>
               <item>That the vnitee of any thynge can not bee denied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the deniall of what ſo euer is included or conteined therin. Cap. 25.</item>
               <item>That the vnitee of Chriſtes perſon can not bee denied, without the denial, bothe of his deitee, and alſo of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitee. Cap. 26.</item>
               <item>After what ſorte diuerſe heretikes haue ſuffered death in certayn poyntes of the feythe. Cap. 27.</item>
               <item>That no credence is to be geuen to their iudgement, whiche thinke an heretike ſo erre in no more of the feithe, but in thoſe pointes, whiche he doth directly denie. C. 28.</item>
               <item>Whether he that ſaieth in his herte, There is no God, denieth god directly, or conſequently, and whether a man maie thynke that he hym ſelfe is not ware of, or no. Capitulo. 29.</item>
               <item>That to denie god but conſequently, is proued by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be no leſſe euill, than it is, to denie hym directly. Capitulo. 30.</item>
               <item>Howe it maie ſtande together, that all heretikes deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the trewth of all the whole feithe, and yet graunt and confeſſe ſo many articles therof as thei dooe. Cap. 31.</item>
               <item>That an heretikes graunt of the trewthe, is not like an other mannes graunt therof. Cap. 32.</item>
               <item>That a directe graunt can not ſtande with a deniall conſequent. Cap. 33.</item>
               <item>That before god, there is no differrence betwene an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent and a conſequent, that is to ſaie betwene before and after. Cap. 34.</item>
               <item>That farre wors is he, that directly denieth but ſome parte of the feithe, than is he that directly denieth all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Cap. 35.</item>
               <item>That the trewthe of Chriſte is no oftener denied in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny articles, than in one alone: and therfore no more
<pb facs="tcp:3752:5"/>
faute is the one than the other. Cap. 36.</item>
               <item>That he whiche denieth Chriſte directly, dooeth it no more ware and wittyngly, then dooeth he, whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth hym but conſequently. Cap. 37.</item>
               <item>What the continewall indeuor of heretikes is, and what ſucceſſe thei haue therin. Cap. 38.</item>
               <item>That heretikes doe good, and therof take hurte. more ouer howe ſtrangely thei worke, and after what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Cap. 39.</item>
               <item>That although heretikes dooe no miracles, yet thei doe ſhewe meruailes. Cap. 40.</item>
               <item>That heretikes taunte vs with commune fautes, to thintente thei might therby cloke and hide the reſte of their owne propre and ſpeciall fautes. Cap. 41.</item>
               <item>What fruictes thei be, whiche Chriſt our ſauior doothe teache vs to knowe heretikes by. Cap. 42.</item>
               <item>Whether a generall deſcripcion of heretikes can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe heretikes or no. Cap. 43.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:5"/>
               <head>¶An introduction of the matter. Cap. 1.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>CATHOLICVS,</speaker>
                  <p>Hearke I ſaie cuntreman, a worde with the.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RETICVS.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake ye to me ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What queſtion is that, where there is none, but hou and I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What woulde ye with me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I tell the?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>At your pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Trewly, When I ſawe the cumminge this wai alone, thou madeſt me therwith verie gladde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Doutles becauſe I haue bene a greate while verie deſirous to talke with the.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>With me ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye with the. And yet coulde I neuer finde the tyme and place, but by reaſon of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, or one thinge or other, there was alwaie ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to interrupt and let my purpoſe? Therfore now, while it hath chaunced vs, thus luckily (as I hope) here to meete in this quiete place, where there be no ſuche impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentes, but that we maie ſaie, thou to me, and I to the, what ſo euer ſhall like vs beſt: I ſhall for my part (if thou wilt abide and harken well to me) ſhowe the ſome thinges, perchaunce not a litle beyonde thine expectacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir of ſuch thinges, wolde I be gladde to here. But yet I meruaile greatly, that ye ſhoulde be ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to talke with me. For I ſuppoſe ye knowe me not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes well enoughe, by ſight and here ſaie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>why, what haue ye herde of me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In verie dede, I will not longe hide it from the. How be it thou knoweſt, that deliberacion geueth ſomtime, a great occaſion of wiſdome: where as haſte doeth oft times the contrarie. For that thinge, whiche a man doothe ſome
<pb facs="tcp:3752:6"/>
tyme iudge, well and mete to be doone or ſaide at the firſte, by furder leiſure and deliberacion taken therin, he perceiueth at length to be farre otherwiſe, whiche I do now finde by experience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall tell the. When I was firſt moued and be came deſirous to commune &amp; talke with the (letted hitherto as I haue ſhowed the) I did then inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue aſked of the a certaine queſtion, which I perceue now (by reaſon of a more deliberate conſideration conceiued ſince in the meane ſpace) had ben but very ſuperfluous and to no purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAHT.</speaker>
                  <p>what auaileth it, to aſke a queſtion of him, which can not tell the trewthe therof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Thinke ye that in me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is the queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue tolde the a cauſe why, it were but in vayne to ſhow the.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>yet I pray you, ſince ye haue gone ſo farre with all, let me here it, and it were but for my fantaſie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>So maiſt thou dooe and neuer the nere. How be it I will not ſticke with the, for more then that. And therfore the queſtion is this, I had thought than, to haue aſked the, whether thou be an heretike or not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is a ſtraunge queſtion to me, but yet neuertheleſſe, doo you thinke that I can not tell the trewth therof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke ſo in dede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then who can dooe it, if I can not, ſpecially when it tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth me onely, and no man els?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>yet who ſo euer can, ſure it is that thou canneſt not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe ther is no heretike, that can tell whether he be an heretike or not.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 2.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>A ſir, well concluded. For now I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceue ye take me for an heretike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3752:6"/>
not ſo. But yet for ſo muche as I haue herde the often reported, to be an excedyng great fauourer and defender of Frith, and fayne wolde knowe the crewthe therof, thinkyng (at the firſte) that no man coulde tell me better then thou thy ſelfe: I thought therfore then, to haue aſked the queſtion of the, and of no man els. But vpon farder conſideracion therof had, becauſe I nowe finde no man more, nor yet ſo muche vnable, to anſwere the queſtion as thou art in dede: I therfore thought to paſſe it ouer, and not to trouble the with all, at this tyme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but coulde ye none other wiſe inquere of me, whether I were a fauourer of Frith or not, but to aſke me, whether I be an heretike or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is no matter, for all is one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Then can I gather no leſſe of your ſaiynge, but that ye take (at the leaſt) Frith or me, For an heretike, or els bothe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede thou haſt hit me therin, with ſuche a trewth, as I am not able to auoide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſyr, I will be plaine with you, how ſo euer ye take it, Frith was a man, whom I loued with all my herte, and ſhall doe while I liue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I loue the, for that, neuer the better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>And I loue my ſelfe neuer the worſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou canneſt not tell that. For the ſcripture dooeth ſaie.<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Qui diligit iniquitatem, odit animam ſuam.</hi> He that loueth iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, hath his own ſoule. And yet many a one, that ſo doth, thinketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to loue their own ſoules well enough. But neuertheleſſe, credence is to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſcripture, what ſo euer thei ſaie or thinke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Thinke you, that I loue iniquitee, in that I loue Frith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke ſo in dede, if thou loue him (as I beleue thou doeſt) for his hereticall opinions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>A ha, then it is playne enough, that ye take hym for an heretike.
<pb facs="tcp:3752:7"/>
For what maketh an heretike but heriticall opinions?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothynge els, that I knowe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fayne wolde I here of you, what heriticall opinions ye can fynde in hym, to proue hym an heretike by.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Before we come to that, let vs firſte (as I thynke it beſte) ſerche, trie, and proue, what the ſtate of an heretike is. That vpon the knowlage of what caſe or condicion he liueth in, we maie the better perceiue, what he is, and conſequently whether Frith were any ſuche or no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>With that I am content.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the firſte notable thynge, that I fynde in the ſtate of an heretike is this, that it is not poſſible for hym to knowe, that he is an heretike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>I meruaile great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what ſhuld moue you to be of that opinion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Trewly I haue therein, none opinion at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than do ye ſpeake it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Not becauſe of any opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, but becauſe I do certainly know it, which paſſeth opinion. And therfore, becauſe thou thinkeſt the matter ſo ſtraynge, I wyll adde vnto it this much more, that there is none of them, that dooeth or can ſo muche as beleue or thinke, that him ſelfe is an heretike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What not ſo muche as beleue or thinke it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>It is to farre againſt reaſon, for any man maie thinke, what ſo euer he luſte, whether it be trewe or falſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art therin muche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. For all though, to thinke and to beleue may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all one, yet to thinke &amp; to imagine, are not both one. For thou maiſt imagine, all ſteples and towers to haue ſpronge out of the grounde as trees doe: and alſo euery thynge to be otherwiſe then thou knoweſt it is, if thou wilt. But yet thou canſt not ſo thinke or beleue, although thou woldeſt neuer ſo fayne. For thou canſt not (if thou
<pb facs="tcp:3752:7"/>
marke it well) beleue or thinke any thyng, againſt thine owne knowlage. But yet for all that, Thou maieſt ſo imagine alwaie at thy pleaſure. Whereof it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth playne, that imaginacion is one, and thinkynge or beleuyng is an other. Therfore although an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike maie imagine hym ſelfe to be an heretike, (as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce he will not) yet (as I ſaide) he can neuer (for all that) ſo beleue or thinke, although he wolde. Muche leſſe then, is he able to knowe it. And who therfore wolde aſke hym the queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 3.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet maie he as ſoone beleue and alſo knowe that, as I can beleue you, when ye ſaie that he can not, excepte ye ſhewe me ſome good reaſon why.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou muſt nedes graunt me this, that there is no man an heretike, but becauſe he beleueth amiſſe in ſome parte of the faithe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is trewe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore if he coulde beleue that he were an heretike, than might he beleue that thynge, whiche he doeth not beleue, and that bothe at once, whiche were impoſſible. For it is not poſſible for a man to beleue any thynge, to be euen than any other wiſe than he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth beleue it is. As thus, ſuppoſe one ſo wicked, as to beleue our ſauior Chriſt to be but onely a pure man, and not alſo very god: as in tyme paſte, ſome heretikes did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What of that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen this, if he that ſo beleueth, coulde beleue, that he were therin (as he is in dede) an heretike, he ſhulde than beleue and thinke, that he beleued therin amiſſe. Wherfore, if he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
<pb facs="tcp:3752:8"/>
and thinke, that he beleueth amiſſe, in that he bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth our ſauiour Chriſte to be but onely a man, plaine it is, that he ſhulde therin beleue hym to be both god and man, whan he doth thinke hym ſelfe to beleue amiſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuyng the contrarie: and ſo ſhuld he beleue &amp; not beleue one thynge both at once, which (as I ſaide) is impoſſible. wherfore it muſt nedes folowe, that an heretike can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beleue or thinke, that hym ſelfe is an heretike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr I doe nowe ſomewhat perceiue the thynge my ſelfe. For if I be nat deceiued, it is lyke, as if you did beleue and verily thinke the great Turke to be now here in Englande in dede, it were not poſſible for you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, that ye beleue therin amiſſe, whan your beleue is vtterly, that it is euen ſo. For whan ye beleue, that he is in Englande, if ye coulde beleue, that ye beleued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in amiſſe, than might ye beleue, that he were not in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, whan ye beleue hym to be in it, and ſo ſhulde ye beleue and not beleue one thynge (as ye ſaide) bothe at once, whiche I perceiue were agaynſt all reaſon and trewthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Doutles thou ſpeakeſt herein veray well to the purpoſe, and that perchaunce wolde yet more playnly appere by this. Beleue is ſuche a thynge, as can neuer wittyngly be deceiued, for as ſoone as thou dooeſt thynke, that thou beleueſt in any thynge amiſſe, furthe with in the ſame inſtant thy beleue therin is clene altered and chainged, and is not the ſame that it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And therfore becauſe hereſie is none other, but in ſome parte of the faithe, a miſſebeleue, and a miſſe beleue is not poſſible to be perceiued of hym, in whom it is: it muſt nedes folowe, that no heretike can beleue or thinke that hym ſelfe is an heretike, becauſe he can not beleue or thinke, that he beleueth therin amiſſe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3752:8"/>
               <head>Cap. 4.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir this is nowe farre from the nede of any more probacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but yet, thou ſeeſt not all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou marke it well, this concluſion maie take awaie no ſmall wonder from many men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>what wonder is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Trewly what ſhuld be the cauſe of the rare and ſeldome amendment of heretikes: wherof partly hath ſpronge this comune opinion, that hereſie, franſie, &amp; ieloſie be three diſeaſes incurable: Not becauſe thei be al vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo in dede, but becauſe they be ſo ſildome ſene, to bee throughly cured &amp; healed ageyne. And ſpecially of hereſy, what wonder is it, although it be ſeldome or neuer forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; amended? wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is (as thou haſt now herde) to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heretike (as to one in a continuall traunce) vtterly vnknowne &amp; incredible, that him ſelfe is any thinge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with infected. for he thinketh verily, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is in the ſtreight waie, not remembringe therof, what the holy ſcripture ſaieth, <hi>Eſt via que videtur homini recta,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; nouiſſima eius ducunt ad mortem,</hi> That is to ſaie, There is a waie whiche ſeemeth to a man ſtreighte, and yet the endes therof leadeth hym to perdicion. And therfore who can expell and put that awaie from him, whiche he can not beleue that euer it came nere hym? who can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to be healed of that infirmitee, wherwith he can not thynke that euer he was diſeaſed? or who can be willing for to amende, wherin he can not ſo muche as thinke, that euer he did offende, ſpecially whan we may dayly ſee the amendemet of manifeſte euils, very ſeldome or neuer brought to paſſe in ſome, whan they bothe beleue and knowe them ſelues to be infected with them. Yet muche eaſier it is (be it neuer ſo harde) to leaue and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende
<pb facs="tcp:3752:9"/>
that is perceiued and knowne amiſſe, than it is (be it neuer ſo eaſie) to auoide and forſake that, which is cleane hid, vnknowne, and incredible. Who therfore, or what can purge, cure, or heale this moſt perelous and inſenſible ſicknes, but only the great mercie of him, which of a blinde and crewell perſecutour, made a moſte paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and excellent preacher?<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> but how ſhuld his moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull medicine be opteined, where it is neuer deſired? and howe can it be deſired, where the cauſe why, nother is, nor can be perceiued? By this therfore thou maiſte haue ſome vnderſtanding of the lamentable ſtate of an heretike, who of all men is in moſte daunger: and yet fardeſt of, from all good remedie, helpe, or ſuccour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Haue you any worſe to ſaie of him than that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede I haue more, whether it be worſe or no, I will referre that to thy iudgement, if thou wilt tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the hearing therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes ſir that will I doe, if this daie will ſerue the turne.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 5.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then what wilt thou ſaie, if this felowe be he, whom the prophet doeth meane, where he ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Dixit inſipiens in cordo ſuo, non eſt deus,</hi> The fooliſhe man ſaide in his herte, there is no god?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What heretike can we finde or reade of, that euer ſaide in his herte there is no god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken whiche of them thou wilt, thou canſte not chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>By that, ye will make it euery one of theim.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not make it, but ſo it is for all that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>It were harde to make me beleue it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>The due order of inuincible reaſon, ſhall bringe the to it, if thou wilt ſtande to that: For the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3752:9"/>
of the thinge, is eaſie to be made, ye and (ſoberly herde) more eaſie to be vnderſtande.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>When I here it, I will tell you more of my minde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Of this thou art aſſured by the ſcripture before alleged, that ſome there be, which ſaie in the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, there is no god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That I dooe now take to be trew, For els the ſcripture wolde not ſpeake therof, as it dooeth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore what other thinge is it, to ſaie in the herte, there is no god, then euen ſecretly in the herte, to denie god?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I take that to be all one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou ſo doo, thou takeſt it right. And therfore becauſe it is ſure, that Chriſt is very god him ſelfe, it muſte nedes folow, that he, whiche denieth god in his herte, denieth Chriſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Of that concluſion, faine wolde I here ſome better proſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>An other thou maieſt, but no better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then an other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſhalbe this. Thou knoweſt (I ſuppoſe) that Chriſt in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe places of ſcripture,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> is declared to be (as he is in dede) the very ſonne, of god the father?<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 1.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is trew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And euen ſo is this, that he, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth god, denieth any ſuche father, for that which is not, can be no father. And he that denieth any ſuche father, denieth alſo therin any ſuche ſonne. For no ſuche ſonne can be, of no ſuche father, nor no ſuche father can be, of no god. And therfore of no ſuche father and no ſuche ſon, muſt nedes folowe no Chriſte, for he were not Chriſte, if he were not the verie and onely ſonne of god, whom in the hert, (as the ſcripture ſaith) the fooliſh felowe denieth. And therfore conſequently euen Chriſte alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I perceue and graunt the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then furder ſaieth the dew order of reaſon this, that he, whiche denieth Chriſt, denieth the verie trewth of all his whole
<pb facs="tcp:3752:10"/>
feith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Perchaunce that maie be trewe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no chaunce in that point, for it is more playne, then ſhall nede any farder probacion. And therfore he, which denieth the trewth of all the whole faithe, denieth therin ſome part therof, or els he could not deni the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is out of all queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then muſte this folowe, that he whiche denieth the trewth of any parte of the faith, denieth therin the trewthe of all the whole.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 6.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That I muſt nedes denie, becauſe it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with not. for although this muſt nedes folowe, that he which denieth the trewth of all the whole, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth therin ſome parte therof, yet (of the other ſide) it is not poſſible for this to folowe, that he whiche denieth ſome part therof, denieth therin the trewth of all together. for theſe two latter propoſicions, can neuer be conuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>what meaneſt thou, by propoſicions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertible?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Two ſaienges, wherof eache muſte nedes folowe other, put before or behinde, which of them ye will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And doeſt thou thinke, that theſe two, be none of them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I thynke ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou arte therin deceiued: For they be conuertible in dede, and ſo are all the reſte that went before, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe two, doo iuſtly folowe. And that ſhalt thou ſee ſtreight, for I will go backward with them again, and begin with this, whiche thou ſhalt not denie: who ſo euer is an heretike, he denieth ſome parte of the faith at the leaſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>That is trewe. for els he were no heretike at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And who ſo euer denieth any part of the faith, denieth therin the trewth therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſte
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3752:10"/>
nedes graunt that alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And who ſo euer deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the trewth of any part of the faithe, denieth therin the trewthe of all the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That I muſte and will (as I ſaide) vtterly denie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then muſte I proue it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERET.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea ſir if ye can: but I thinke it will be a good while firſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it ſhall be longe of the. For if all the trewthe, of all the whole feith be conteined in euery parte therof, who can auoide this, but he that denieth any parte therof, denieth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the trewthe of all the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye ſyr if it be ſo, but firſte proue, that it is ſo, And then afterwarde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude as ye may.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſhall nede no very great profe, after a certaine declaration made, of ſuche three thynges, as I ſhall ſhewe the.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 7.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Whiche be thoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſte is, what is more then trewthe. The ſeconde is, what is leſſe then trewthe. The thirde is, what is other then trewthe. Theſe three, that is to witte, more then trewthe, leſſe then trewthe, and other then trewthe, are all and eache of them, euen as farre from trewthe, as trewthe it ſelfe is from no trewthe: whiche be directe contraries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſhall this appere?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Uery well and plaine enough. For perticularly, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with the firſt, of this we maie be well aſſured, that trewthe can be no more then trewthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That I muſte nedes graunte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou canſt doe no leſſe. And therfore when trewthe can be no more then trewthe, it muſte nedes folowe, that more then trewthe can be no trewthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERETIC.</speaker>
                  <p>To that I aſſente alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATHOLICVS.</speaker>
                  <p>Then ſecundarily, we bee
<pb facs="tcp:3752:11"/>
likewiſe aſſured of this, that trewthe can be no leſſe then trewthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is more playne, then can be denied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore whan trewth can be no leſſe then trewth: as plaine it is, that leſſe then trewth, can be no trewthe nother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>To that I muſte nedes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then thirdly we maie not doubte, that trewth can be any other then trewth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is out of all queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore when trewthe can be none other than trewth, doth it not therfore iuſtly folowe, that other then trewthe, can be no trewthe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſyr, all this hitherto, I wyll not denie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then to the purpoſe, and as touchyng the firſt, if the trewthe of the whole feithe, were any more, then the trewthe of the leaſt parte of it, then were it more then trewthe. For the trewthe of the leaſte parte is trewthe, and trewe to be more then trewthe, is all ready proued impoſſible. Wherfore the trewthe of the whole feith, can be no more, then the trewth of the leſt parte of it. Agein, for the ſeconde, by lyke reaſon, if the trewthe of the leaſt parte of it, were any leſſe, then the trewthe of the whole feithe, then were it leſſe then trewthe. For the trewthe of the whole, is trewthe: but trewthe to bee leſſe then trewthe, is well knowne can neuer bee. Therfore the trewthe of the leaſt parte of the feithe, is no leſſe, then the trewthe of all the whole. Now thirdly, if the trewthe of any one parte, were not the very ſame, but an other, then the trewthe of any other parte: then were it an other then trewth. For the trewth of any other parte is trewth, and trewth to be any other then trewth, is ſcant imagina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. Wherfore there can be none other trewthe, in any one parte of the feithe, than there is in any of the other, or in all the reſte together. Therfore becauſe the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3752:11"/>
of any one parte of the feithe, is none other but the deniall of the trewthe therof. And whan there is no more, no leſſe, nor none other trewthe in all the whole feithe, then is in euery ſingular parte therof: it muſte nedes folowe, that who ſo euer denieth any parte of the feithe, denieth therin the trewthe of all the whole. And ciere it is, that he whiche denieth the trewthe of all the whole feithe, denieth Chriſte: And he that denieth Chriſte, denieth god. And thus doth euery heretike with out faile. Wherfore of euery one of theim all, theſe woordes of the prophet, The fooliſhe felowe ſaide in his herte, there is no god, maie well and trewly be verified.<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 3.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr I beleue this matter wyll yet trouble vs bothe, ere we parte, for all this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe there cometh nowe to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, ſuche, and ſo many thynges to the contrarie, as maketh me thinke, that all this can not holde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then thou haſte but a ſclender wit, or a fickell mynde, that will ſo quickly be moued, or with any thyng allured, from ſo well approued trewthe, as this is. Thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt rather haue ſaide, that there cometh many thingꝭ to thy remembrance, whiche cauſeth the to maruell, howe thei with this can agree together: becauſe there is no trewth in any one thynge, that can be againſt the trewth of any other. For trewth againſt trewth, is no more to ſaie, but trewthe ageinſt it ſelfe, whiche is not poſſible. Therfore if theſe thynges, whiche nowe ſo cometh (as thou ſaieſt) to thy remembrance be trewe, doubtles they with this, maie ioigne and agree together well enough, although thy knowlage can not ſee how. Of thother ſide,
<pb facs="tcp:3752:12"/>
if thei be not trewe, thei muſt be reiected and refuſed: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this, by them or any other like, can not be auoided. Wherfore to exclude all maner of tergiuerſacion herein to come, let this, whiche is (as thou haſt herde) ſo dewly proued all redie, be fully agreed and ſtabliſhed betwene vs in the meane tyme, as a moſt ſure truthe and grounde to reſte vpon: or at the leaſte, till thou haſt founde ſome good cauſe why, it ought not ſo to be taken. which I am ſure thou canſt not dooe. And therfore, let me now here what thynges thoſe be, whiche moueth me to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr I will tell you. And firſte for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the reſurrection of Chriſte, ye knowe is one parte of the feithe, and thaſcenſion is an other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>All that is playne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERET.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, if the veray ſame trewth, no more, no leſſe, nor none other, were in the one article that is in the other, it muſte nedes folowe, that the reſurrection and the aſcencion ſhulde bee bothe one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERET.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye wyll not denie, but when I ſaie Chriſte roſe from death to lyfe, I ſaie trewthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What els?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>And when you ſaie, that he aſcended, you ſaie truthe likewiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then if theſe bee not two diſtincte truthes, but are bothe one, ſo that the one is none other, but euen the very ſame that the other is, then ſaie you the very ſame that I doe. And I the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſame that you dooe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but what ſame is that? I graunte, I ſaie the ſame trewthe, that thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: but yet not the ſame thyng, wherin the ſame truth is. But thou takeſt the trewthe (I perceiue) &amp; the thynges, wherin it is, to be all one. And therfore becauſe the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges differ, thou thinkeſt the trewthe in them to differ likewiſe, which is not ſo: for if the trewthe of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3752:12"/>
were not the ſame, but an other then the trewthe of the aſcenſion, it ſhulde be an other then trewthe: And trewth to be an other then trewthe, I tolde the before can neuer be. For an other then trewth, is no trewth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſith it can not be an other, it muſte nedes be the ſame. And therfore who ſo euer denieth the trewthe of the one article, denieth therin the trewth of the other. And ſo (as I ſaide) of all together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet is it ſtraunge to me, that one trewthe, whiche hath in it (as ye ſaie) no difference at all, ſhulde be in bothe tharticles, whiche haue a difference.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And well ſpoken, for euen ſo ſtraunge it is, as the onely truthe of the reſurrection, whiche hath no difference, is in all trewe Chriſten hertꝭ at once, whiche haue a difference, and that of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes mo then we can tell. Therfore wilt thou ſaie, that the trewth therof, whiche is in one herte, is not the ſame in eache of the reſte, becauſe thei are ſo many and diuerſe? Dooeſt thou not knowe, that one thinge maie be comunely knowne of thouſandes at once?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes that is plaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And nothynge can bee knowne, but by the trewth therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunte the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAHT.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it muſt nedes folowe, that the ſame one trewth, maie be in a thouſande heades at once. And therfore why not one trewthe, in many articles at once likewiſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but ſir, ye muſte conſider, that althoughe this one trewthe of the reſurrection, bee in your heade and mine bothe: yet it is not the trewthe of your head, nor of mine nother, but of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge. And therfore becauſe (of and in) are two thinges, whiche maketh no litle difference, I ſaie, the trewthe of the reſurrection, allthoughe it bee in your heade and myne, as it is in many thouſandes
<pb facs="tcp:3752:13"/>
mo, yet it is not the trewthe of your head or mine, or of anie other beſide, but of that ſame one article only, and of none other. for although the trewth of one thing maie be in an other, yet it can not be the trewth of an other.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 9.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede thy talke renneth from one thinge to an other, for when our purpoſe in this caſe, is no more but to proue the ſame trewth to be in one arcicle, that is in an other, and ſo in the reſt of them all together, ſtreight thou leapeſt from the onely being of the trewth, vnto the perteinyng or belonging therof: as thoughe we ſought, wherof the trewth ſhulde be, and not, whether the being therof in diuerſe thinges at once, maketh in, or of it ſelfe, any diuerſitee or difference, or no: when that is herein our purpoſe, and nothing els: vnto the whiche, I adde alſo this, that trewth, wherin or wherof, ſo euer it be, is yet no more nor leſſe, nor none other, then trewth, without any maner of diuerſitee: for it is not but one pure ſingle, ſimple, &amp; indiuiſible thing, of this nature &amp; proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, that although there be nothing, whiche dooeth not perticipate the ſame, yet the numeroſitee or bigneſſe of thinges, wherin it is, (be they neuer ſo many or greate) can not make it any mo, or more: Nor the paucitee or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telnes of thinges, any fewer, or leſſe. Nor yet the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitee or alteracion of thinges, any other or otherwiſe, but euen one and the ſame trewth ſtille, as euery where it is, and alway hath bene, and euer ſhall. Therfore, who ſo euer denieth a part of that, which hath no partes (as the trewth it ſelfe hath not in dede) other he denieth all the whole, becauſe the very ſame, which ſemeth a part, is no leſſe but all the whole, or els he denieth therof nothing at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3752:13"/>
all, becauſe that, whiche ſemeth a parte, is therof no part at all. And ſuche (as I ſaide) is the trewth of the faith: which althoughe it haue no partes in dede, yet I will not ſaie, but partes it ſemeth to haue, &amp; that is onely by reaſon of the diuerſitee of tharticles, wherin it is. And not in reſpect of it ſelfe, whiche is whole (as I ſaide) in the whole feith, And yet neuer the leſſe whole alſo in euery ſingular parte therof. And therfore becauſe it is in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſingular article, whiche are diuerſe and many, it is thought (of ſuche as vnderſtande it not) that it ſelfe alſo is diuerſe and many likewiſe: which (as it dothe by reaſon apere) is nothing ſo. wherfore when that, which an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike denieth in any parte of the faith, is not nothing, but with out queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome what in dede. And when that ſame ſome what, can be no part of that, whith hath no partes, it muſte nedes folow, that the ſame, which he denieth, is no leſſe then al the whole: And that is none other but only trewth, wherof the whole feith can haue no more, then the leaſt part of it hath: And therfore in that part, which he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nieth; he denieth the whole trewth of all the whole faith: wherof this muſte alſo folow, that all heretikꝭ are dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, not only in thoſe articles, whiche they directly denie, but alſo in thoſe, whiche they ſeme and thinke them ſelues to graunte, as here after it ſhall more plainly appere.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 10.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I ſhall ſaie to the contrary, more then perchance wil like you to here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I care not for that: And therfore ſpare not, ſaie what thou wilte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I tolde you before, that the trewthe of one thinge, can not be the trewthe of an other: what ſaie you to that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaie to it this: if thou haddeſt ſaid as
<pb facs="tcp:3752:14"/>
much of the propre being of any thing, wherby it is made not the ſame that an other thinge is, I wold haue holden well with all. For in dede the propre beeing of one thing, can not be the propre beeing of an other. But to ſaie, that the trewth of one thing, can not be the trewth of an other, is euen as trewe, as it is to ſaie, that the name of one thing, can not be the name of an other: when moſte manifeſt and commune experience doeth declare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not denie, but that the name of one thing, maie be the name of an other. As Iohn maie be &amp; is the name of two men, and of many mo: yet in whom it chaunceth ſo to bee, there is Iohn and Iohn at the leaſt. But Iohn and Iohn can be no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two, &amp; two can be no leſſe then one &amp; another: And betwene one &amp; on other, there muſt nedꝭ be ſome difference: wherfore, there is a difference, betwene Iohn and Iohn. And euen ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there is, betwene the trewth of one thinge, and the treuth of an other. for betwene two articles, if thei be both trew, ther can be no leſſe, then trewth and truth: alſo truth and truth can be no leſſe then two: And two (as I ſaide) can be no leſſe then one and an other: &amp; betwene one and an other, ther muſt nedꝭ be a difference. Wherfore ther is a difference betwene the trewthe of one article, and the trewthe of an other: and this is directly ageinſt all that ye haue ſaid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>yea but yet becauſe all that I haue ſaid, is well proued and fortified by inuincible reaſon, it is meete to trie, whether all that thou haſte ſaide herein, maie be ſo proued likewiſe or not, as I wot it can not: for where thou ſaieſt, that Iohn and Iohn can be no leſſe then two: what two meaneſte thou (two men, or two names? If thou meane two men, it is nothing to the purpoſe. If thou meane two names,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3752:14"/>
whiche be they?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Iohn and Iohn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>and is Iohn and Iohn two names?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>it is one and an other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is falſe: for Iohn and Thomas, is one and an other, where as Iohn and Iohn, is but one and the ſame, which differeth muche, from one and an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For one and an other maketh diuerſitee: but one and the ſame, can neuer paſſe vnitee. Wherfore as it is betwene Iohn, the name of one man, &amp; Iohn the name of an other: euen ſo it is likewiſe, betwene the trewth of one article and the trewth of an other: wherin I graunt there is trewth and trewth, and yet not one and an other (whiche as I ſaide maketh diuerſitee) but one and the ſame, which paſſeth not vnitee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet ſith ye graunt that there is trewthe and trewth, if there were therin no difference nor diuerſitee, what doeth this worde (and) betwene them, whiche is a copulatiue and ioigneth two together?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therin thou muſte conſider, that this worde (and) doth not ſo couple trewthe and trewthe together, in ſuche ſorte as thou takeſt it. Forhere, trewth in the ſeconde place, is but the only repeticion of the ſame in the firſt place: and the repeticion of a thynge, in reſpect that it is a repeticion, doeth alwaie ſomewhat differ from the thyng it ſelfe, which is repeted, as it doeth clerely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere by this, that the one maie be without the other: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this copulatiue (and) doth ioigne together truth, and the repeticion of the ſame, and not trewthe and trewthe, as two ſundrie thinges, whiche in dede is but one repeted agein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr although this be pretily excuſed, yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaide, ther is trewth in the reſurrection and trewth in thaſcencion, truth in the ſeconde place ther, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt place: becauſe there is nother re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor yet repeticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, but only a demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracion
<pb facs="tcp:3752:15"/>
and a ſhewyng wherin it is. And yet there, the copulatiue doeth ioigne them together neuer the leſſe. Wherfore thei are, and muſt nedes be of ſome difference.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art yet deceiued. For there, the copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue hath reſpect to tharticles, ioignyng them together, in the poſeſſion of trewthe, and in the reherſall of the ſame: And not to the trewthe, whiche in them both is but one in reſpecte of it ſelfe. For where it is ſaide, there is trewthe in the reſurrection, and trewthe in thaſcencion, doubtles the very ſame ſentence maie as well be ſaide in theſe woordes: The reſurrection, and thaſcencion, haue the trewth in eache of them: wherin it doth well appere, what the copulatiue ioigneth together: And that is not trewthe and trewthe, whiche is all one: But one arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and an other, whiche are no leſſe then twaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet all this doth not ſatiſfie me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art perchaunce one of thoſe, that will not bee ſatiſfied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Naie ſir I am none of theim.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 11.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then becauſe thou doeſt wade ſo farre in the matter, tell me what is the trewthe of a thyng?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I myght therin tell you my fantaſie, whiche perchaunce ye wolde not lyke. And therfore I had rather lerne it of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke thou wilt not denie, but that the trewthe of any thynge, is what ſo euer maie trewly be ſaide therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then wyll I ſaie this, that of any thynge it maie trewly be ſaide, that it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſaieſt well therin: And therfore the ſame at the leaſt, is the trewthe therof. For if the thynge wer not, this coulde neuer be trewe, to ſaie it is. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, name thou ſome certaine thyng, wherin this trewth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3752:15"/>
maie appere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye maie name what ye will, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were but a ſticke or a ſtone, it is enough (as I thinke) for the purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then a ſtone be it, if thou wilt. For of a ſtone, as of any other thynge, it muſt nedes be trewe, that it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>That is out of queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore if this trewthe of beyng, were not in the ſtone, wilt thou ſaie, that the ſtone coulde bee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERET.</speaker>
                  <p>No not ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And is not euen that ſame trewthe, in, and of an other ſtone, as well as in, or of, this or that ſtone, yea and of euery ſtone beſide like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>In that I will no farder contende.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore, why ſaieſt thou, that the trewth of one thynge can not be the trewthe of an other, when this is plaine, that a flint ſtone is one thynge, and a marbell ſtone is an other. And yet maieſt thou here clerely perceiue and ſee one trewth, in and of them both: and verifieth the beyng, not onely as well of the one as of the other: but alſo of all other thynges beſide, of what ſorte or kynde ſo euer thei bee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Naie then, if it be ſo, that one trewthe doe (as who ſaie) inhabite all maner of thynges (as you ſaie now it doth in dede) I praie you tell me, how cometh this to paſſe, that ſo great peigne, labor, and trauell, hath euer bene, &amp; daily is taken, in counſailes, courtꝭ, ſcholes, vniuerſities, and diuers other waies, for the ſerche and triall of the trewth? when (if your ſaiyng be trewe) there is no ſorte of men, hauing the vſe of reaſon, but hath it in ſome kynde of thynges all redy. And therfore what wold thei haue more, or what nede any farder labour for it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>although thei haue it alredie in many thynges. Yet they haue it not therfore in all thynges. Amonge the whiche, it is ſone had in ſome of theim, by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And in ſome of theim, not without ſome labour,
<pb facs="tcp:3752:16"/>
but in ſome of them, not without a longe and ſtudious diligence, and that ſpecially in diuers caſes of lernyng: by reaſon wherof, ther is oft times had in ſchooles many great &amp; graue diſputacions: and for the fortifiyng of the dewe order of reaſon therin (by the whiche the trewthe ſo trauailed for, muſt nedes be gotten, or els it wyll not be had) there are brought in many ſundrie and ſtronge prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and rules, whiche beare in them ſelfes, ſuche an ineuitable and manifeſt trewthe, as no man with reaſon, can or will denie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir I praie you ſtaie there a while. For this will I ſaie, that if there be amonge all thoſe principles and rules, whiche ye ſpeake of, any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitee of trewth, that is to ſaie, any other trewth in any one of them, then there is in any of the other, or in all to gether: then haue I my purpoſe. Of the other ſide, if ther be no diuerſitee of trewth among them, but that the ſame trewth, whiche is in any one of them, is alſo in eache of the other and in all to gether, then are thei all, (one except at the moſt) but euen vaine and very ſuperfluous: when that ſame one, hath none other, but the very ſame and as muche trewthe in it, as hath all the reſte beſide. And therfore that one were enough and ſufficient of it ſelfe without nede of any moe, but euen of that alone: and yet not of that nother, if it be well weighted. For when that ſerueth but only to the findyng &amp; obteinyng of the trewth, which is (as you ſay, had in the ſame &amp; ſome other thyngꝭ all redy, what is it els but as though I might goe ſeke that thyng in the felde, whiche I am ſure of before in my chambre? And therfore if ther be but one truth, in all and euery thynge that is: &amp; euery man hath the ſame all redie in one thynge or other: vaine &amp; ſuperfluous are all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, courtꝭ, ſcoles, diſputacions, inquiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſerches &amp; ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3752:16"/>
other induſtrious indeuers, made for thobteining therof.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 12.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Depely reaſoned and well fro the purpoſe: for I haue tolde the already, that although they haue it in ſome thinges, yet thei haue it not in all thinges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that to the purpoſe? for when thei haue it all redie, what nede they ſeeke (as I ſaied) any farder for it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I perceiue it plaine, that litle doeſt thou conſider, how diuerſly trewth (which is not diuerſe) in diuerſe thinges behaueth it ſelfe: for returne thy conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracion but euen to ſtones ageine, and of the which, thou ſhalt perceiue in ſome, the trewth to ſhow it ſelfe ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, that no man douteth of what ſorte or kinde they be. And in ſome, it kepeth it ſelfe ſo priuely, that few me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the verie trewe ſtone from a counterfeit, except he be a good lapidarie: Alſo in ſome other kynde of thinges, it behaueth it ſelfe, yet ſo muche more darkely: that it chaunceth to the cource but of fewe men therin to come to it, and yet that not without muche difficultee. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it lieth in diuerſe and many caſes ſo ſecretly, that all the wittes of men, can not atteine to the knowlage ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, excepte it be coniecturally. And yet is it in ſome of them, for vs, and of vs to be had, moſt expedient and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: And therfore amonge them, where the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of mannes witte dooeth faile, it pleaſeth the goodnes of god, that trewe faith, with good zele, ſhall yet catche holde, and therin much preuaile: And therfore, when this is moſt plaine, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath much more gretter nede of trewth, in ſome thinges then in ſome: &amp; ageine, when thoſe thingꝭ wherin he hath moſt nede therof, are of that ſorte, whiche (as who ſaie) kepeth it moſte ſecretly, and
<pb facs="tcp:3752:17"/>
fardeſt from his knowlage and vnderſtandinge, howe ſhulde he therin come by it, but by ſuche wais &amp; meanes, as are moſte mete and conuenient for it? and what wais and meanes ar thoſe, if wit &amp; trewth be not two of them? for who, without ſufficient capacitee of wit, can therin pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaile or atteine vnto it? Of the other ſide, who, without trewth, is able to ſeeke, and come by trewth? except thou wilte ſaie, it may be ſought and gotten by falſhed, which is not poſſible: Therfore no man without trewth, is able to ſeeke and come by trewth,<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> ſpecially when theſe be the wordes of trewth, I am the way, trewth, and life.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 13.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>The way, trewth, and life, what are thoſe three, to this purpoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Uery much, if thou marke this well, that the ſpeaker therof, muſte nedes bee one of thoſe three at the leaſte: for when the ſpeaker doth ſay (I am) and declareth what, that is to ſay, the waie, trewth, and life, it can not be auoided, but of the three, trewth at the leaſt (whiche is one of them) muſte nedes be the ſpeaker of it, becauſe it is not poſſible, for this to be trewly ſaide of any ſpeaker (I am the trewth) but euen onely of trewth it ſelfe: And therfore, becauſe trewthe ſaieth alſo here of it ſelfe, that it is the way: it muſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des folowe, that the wey, is the trewth to: for the trewth, could not trewly ſaie, that it ſelfe were the way, excepte the waie were the trewth: And yet more ouer, becauſe it ſaith farder of it ſelfe, that it is the life, the life alſo muſte nedes be the trewth likewiſe, although it beareth here (as the waie doth) an other name: for the trewthe could not trewly ſaie, that it ſelfe were the life, except the life were the trewth. And for ſo much as there is no way,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3752:17"/>
that tendeth not to an ende, clere it is therfore, that this way, muſt nedes haue an ende: wherfore, as this way, which is the way of truth, far paſſeth al maner of waies, euen ſo it muſt nedes haue an ende, farre paſſinge all maner of endes: And becauſe there is no ende compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to perfitte life without ende. Therfore that ſame life, muſt nedꝭ be the ende of this way, and yet not ſo, as though the ſame were not alſo the truth it ſelfe. for when it is playne, that farder then trewth, trewth can not go. Trewth muſt nedes be the ende of trewth alſo, which (as I ſaid) is perfit life without ende. wherfore, this I may well conclude and ſay, that trewth is the way wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and trewth is the beginnyng from whence, and treuth is the ende wherunto, for the which cauſe (as I ſuppoſe) the propre name of trewthe is there placed in the middes betwene the other two, as who ſaith indifferente or the ſame, to and with them bothe. wherfore by this thou maiſt perceue and ſee, that theſe three, ar much to the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, which is to ſhow, that the treuth of one thing, is the the very waie, to come by the trewth of an other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>ye but what nede a man to ſeke it in one thinge, when he hath it all redie in an other?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe he hath (as I ſaied, and as it is plaine) not only much more nede of it in one thing, then he hath in an other, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, for the ſtraieng, and diuerſe behauiour therof, it is therin, more harde to come by, then it is in an other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then ſir all this notwithſtandinge, if the waie, trewth,<note place="margin">Ioan. 14.</note> &amp; life, which are three, be all but euen one trewth, why is it put ſo diuerſly, as though it were otherwiſe?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 14.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That queſtion will make but a digreſſion nothing to my purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>yet it ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:3752:18"/>
ſomwhat to my purpoſe for all that, if ye anſwere it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then for aunſwere take this, thou ſhalt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that trewth, in reſpect of the propre eſſenciall and verie being of it ſelfe, can neither receue either more or leſſe, that is to ſaie, it can neither increaſe, nor decreaſe, augment, or diminiſhe: But yet in reſpect of the beeing therof in mannes vnderſtanding, it maie dooe bothe, as of the one ſide we maie well and eaſily perceue it, by the fruictes and profite of that induſtrie and diligent labour, whiche many beſtoweth about the ſame. For to what intente are children ſette to ſchole? or to what purpoſe doeth all ſtudentes labour and traueil in any ſcience? More ouer, wherfore are all inquiſitions and ſerches made? but onely to come by the more trewth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>For to come by the more knowlage ye maie ſaie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAT.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is knowlage without trewth? ſpecially when this is moſte trewe, that nothinge can be knowne, but onely by the trewth therof. for as the power of ſight with out light, nothinge can dooe, And therfore, no light, no ſight: Euen ſo the power of knowlage without trewthe likewiſe can nothing do nother. And therfore no trewth, no knowlage, except thou wilt cal this knowlage, to take one thinge for an other, or any thing to be otherwiſe then it is, which is in dede but very blinde ignorance, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els: wherfore, who ſo euer ſeketh after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of any thinge, ſeketh in dede nothinge els, but the trewthe therof, whiche obteined, the thinge is knowne, and otherwiſe not. Ageine, who ſo euer ſeeketh the trewthe of any thinge, hath all readie the trewthe, of ſome other thinges, or els it were not poſſible for him to go aboute it, as it maie well appere, by the cauſe why, that yong infantes are not compelled to ſchole, or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3752:18"/>
other feates of knowlage, vnto the tyme, their potencial capacite of trewthe, become to ſome actuall poſſeſſion therof. Therfore becauſe the deligent induſtrie and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of all ſtudentes, of the one ſide, and alſo thintenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all inquiſicions and ſerches, of the other ſide, dothe plainly proue and declare, that ſome men alwaie dooe ſeke after trewth, and that not in vaine, as it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, by that thei do therin more and more increaſe, and daylie obteine. And agein, becauſe they nother wolde, nor coulde ſo dooe, if they had not alredie, the trewth of many thinges before, to ſette them a worke therin: it muſt nedes folowe, that trewth in mans vnderſtandinge doth, and may dayly grow and increaſe more and more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>And what of all this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall tell the what, becauſe this is plaine, that increaſe can neuer bee, but from the leſſe to the more. And agein, for ſo much, as from the leſſe to the more, can be no paſſage, but by a right conuenient meane and waie betwene them. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is man herin ſo taught the waie, that there can be no miſtruſt or any dout therof, when trewth, which can not lie, doeth ſaie of it ſelfe, <hi>I am the waie.</hi> And yet becauſe, ther is lightly no waie, but maie other by the ignorance, or ſome other imperfection of the ſtraieng trauelar ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, be ſoone miſſed and loſte, with out a ſuer guide. Therfore is he taught alſo, to take none other, but euen the ſame to be his guide, which hath trewly told him the waie, becauſe there is none, nor none can be to a man, ſo good and ſure a guide in his iourneie, as the trew teacher therof, whiche is alſo the verie trewthe, as it ſelfe doeth ſaie, when it ſaieth, I am the way. And yet farder more, for ſo much as ther groweth in a iourneie of long and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious labour, ſuch a werineſſe, as might chaunce to cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:3752:19"/>
the trauelar to feint, ſlake, and ceaſſe to continue therin, and ſo to geue ouer his purpoſe, excepte ther be ſome ſuch notable thynge, to be loked for in the ende, as maie well and iuſtly, ſo kindle his deſyre therof, that for the whiche he ſetteth all his labour at nothynge: the trauelar ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the iourney and labour of this waie, is moſt trew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtructed, and throughly aſſured of ſuche a benefite and commoditee to folowe therof, as is of all thynges moſte excellent and in comparable: for what is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to perfecte life without ende, whiche aboue all thynges is moſt deſiderable? And therfore that is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raie ende, where vnto this waie doothe euer more leade and directely tende: wherof the trauellar (if he holde on his iourneie and goe thorowe with all) is moſte aſſured by the promeſſe of no leſſe than the very mouth of trewth it ſelfe, whiche doothe ſaie: <hi>I am the life.</hi> And therfore by this it maie well appere, that in what ſo euer is rightly doone and well brought to paſſe, Trewthe is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, The ende, and alſo the weie betwene them: that is to ſaie, the waie wherin the purpoſe is folowed: The trewth, wherby it is firſt ſet a worke. And the ende, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it is finally brought. And yet all three, no more, no leſſe, nor none other, but euen one trewthe: without the whiche, what is the waie? what is the beginnyng? or what is the ende of any thynge but all vaine and nothing worthe? And therfore to ſhewe, that trewthe is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfection of all and eache of them three, it dothe here ſet furthe and daclare it ſelfe accordyngly with this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite of wordes,<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> ſayng I am the weie, trewth, and life: as muche to ſeie, as without me, There is no weie ſtreight, no beginnyng good: nor no ende profitable. Wherfore nowe thou haſt herde for anſwere to thy queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3752:19"/>
(as I ſuppoſe) a good cauſe why, that trewth, which is but one, is here ſo diuerſely put, as though it were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe: Muche more herof there might be ſeide, but this is enough for the purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 15.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir I am glad I haue herde yow ſaie ſo muche: for ye concluded before, that what ſo euer is more or leſſe then trewthe, can be no trewthe at all. And yet here nowe ye ſaie, it maie be more and more: as your ſaiynges therof dooeth plainly declare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Saied I, more and more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea more and more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Of trewthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is well ſaied: And putteſt thou no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwene more or leſſe of trewthe, And more or leſſe then trewthe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What difference ſhulde I put therin?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſke thine owne eie, wherby thou maieſt lerne it. For by more of light, thou maieſt ſee the better. But by more then light, thou canſt ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge at all. For what is more then light, but vtterly no light? and what is no light, but the contrarie, whiche is veraie darkeneſſe? And agayne, what is leſſe then light, but alſo euen the ſame likewiſe? therfore more or leſſe of light, and more or leſſe then light, are two thyngꝭ. For by more then light, light is excluded: but by more of lighte, lighte is but increaſed. And euen ſo likewiſe of trewthe. For by more then trewthe, trewthe is cleane excluded: but by more of trewth, trewth, (where it maie) is but increaſed. For he that telleth the but parte of a trewe tale, dothe tell the leſſe of the trewthe, then doothe he, that trewly telleth the, the whole tale: And he that tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the, the whole tale, doth tell the more of the trewthe,
<pb facs="tcp:3752:20"/>
then doth he, that telleth the, but parte of it: and yet both trewe. But if thou perceiue, that he dothe tell the more then the trewthe of the whole: or leſſe then the trewthe of any parte: woldeſt thou not take hym for a lier or a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reporter of the matter? Yea and that iuſtely: Becauſe he is no leſſe in dede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then by this, it dothe yet appere, that one article of the feithe maie haue more or leſſe of trewthe, then an other hath.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No not ſo nother, for the trewthe is not ſeied (as I tolde the before) to be other more or leſſe, for any thynge that is in it ſelfe, but onely in reſpecte of and for the numbre of thynges wherin it is, and wherof it is had: Becauſe that ſame numbre of thynges, wherin it is, and wherof it is had, is in owre knowlage, ſomtime more, and ſomtime leſſe. And for that cauſe it is ſeide to bee more or leſſe: and for nothynge els. For when it is ſeide that a man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth more of the trewthe to daie, then be did yeſterdaie, it is not properly to be vnderſtande and taken, that he knoweth more trewthe, but the truthe of more matter, or of mo thynges to daie then he knewe yeſterdaie, and not more of the trewth it ſelfe, whiche can not be, other more or leſſe. And beſide this, although more or leſſe of trewth maie be ſeide in reſpecte of the beyng therof in mannes knowlage, by reaſon of the comyng and goyng of thingꝭ to and fro, as thexperience therof doth declare: yet it can not be ſo ſeide in any other kynde of thynges, which haue no ſuche actiuite or capacite of vnderſtandynge or diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge one thynge from an other, as the priuilege of mannes nature hath. And therfore all this, maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge for thy purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>it is no maruell as ye do handell it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3752:20"/>
               <head>Cap. 16.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>So longe as I handill it acording to truth, there is no faute to be founde therin. And therfore although thou haſt driuen it of, very lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: yet it maie this very well appere, that it is nother vaine nor ſuperfluous, that learned men take with theim in their diſputacions many rules and principles of trewthe, to conducte eyde and kepe the dewe order of reaſon, from all deuiacion and errour, vntill it come as it were to the porte and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall concluſion of that, whiche therby is intended: for as a man hauynge a farre longe, and a ſtrange iourney to trauaile, had nede ſome tyme of ſondrie guides, becauſe it maie chaunce one, whiche can conducte hym twentie myles, can not yet guide hym three ſcore, by reaſon his knowlage of that waie extendeth not ſo farre, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt nedes be had an other, and perchaunce diuerſe moe, after as the caſe requireth: euen ſo mans witte and reaſon, hauynge vrgente occaſion, to ſerche and ſeeke trewthe, in ſuche neceſſary thynges, as kepeth it veraie ſecret, and farre from his knowlage: hath much nede of certain and ſondrie ſuche guides, as are for that purpoſe moſte conuenient and neceſſarie, that is to wit, diffinici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſtinctions, reſpectes, and diuerſe other lyke rules of in fallible trewthe, to leade and conueie it directely from one thynge to an other, vntill it come there, where it obteineth, the ſame it deſyreth. And though there bee therin, none other ſought nor yet founde, but euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raie ſame trewthe, whiche was had before in many thynges: yet is it not laboured in vayne, nor without neede nother, becauſe it was hidde, and not hadde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that one thynge, wherein it was perchaunce, more expediente to bee had, then in diuerſe and many
<pb facs="tcp:3752:21"/>
other thinges beſide: Wherfore, when no man can come to trewthe, but by the wey and meane of trewth (for trewth will in no wiſe be obteyned or towched, but by the way and meane of it ſelfe) why doeſt thou thinke it ſo ſtraunge a matter, that men labour therin, ſo ſore for the ſame which they haue alredy? that is to ſaie, for the ſame trewth in one thinge, whiche they haue alredy in an other, when the trewth of one thing, is the way and meane, to come (as I ſayde) by the trewth of an other. for otherwiſe it will not be had. Wherfore now I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, thou art in this cace, ſufficiently anſwered.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 17</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir let that waie as it maie here after, for I dout not but ye will yet graunte me this, that blacke and white, as in ynke and paper are two diſtincte and contrarie colours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then if there be no more, no leſſe, nor none other, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the very ſame trewth in the blacke, that is in the white, and the ſame in the white, that is in the blacke, why ſhulde it not be as trewe to ſaie, the blacke is white, and the white blacke, as it is to ſay, the blacke is blacke, and the white is white, if there be (as you ſay) but one indifferente trewth of them bothe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no more in dede, but yet becauſe the ſelfe ſame one trewth whiche doth verifie the blacke to be blacke, and the white to be white, is alſo as well in the difference of both thoſe colours, and ſo doth verifie the ſame likewiſe, as it is in eache and both the colours them ſelues, it doeth therfore vtterle forbid it ſo to be ſaide, as thou ſpeakeſt it. becauſe if thou ſay the blacke is white, or the white blacke. The trewth of the difference betweue them, is clerely ageinſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3752:21"/>
the, which trewthe is al one, in al three, as it is and muſt nedes be in all other thinges likewiſe beſide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then will I leue all theſe kindes of thingꝭ, and go to the very ſcripture, which in this cace, is directly ageinſt you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 18.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE:</speaker>
                  <p>haue you not redde in the pſalter,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> wher this is written, <hi>Quoniam diminute ſunt veritates á filiis hominum</hi>? that is to ſaie, trewthes, ar miniſhed from the children of men, or trewthes are falen awey from the children of men. Here ye ſe, it ſpeaketh not of trewth ſingularly, but of trewthes in the pluraln umber, wherin is conteined many, which can not be without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitee, &amp; this is therfore clene ageinſt your ſaieng.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>To this I will firſt anſwere the, with the wordꝭ of Saint Auſten, and afterward as I can beſide. For ſaint Auſten vpon the ſame text, doth ſay this, trewth is one, with the which, holy ſoules are illuſtrate, but becauſe there be (he ſaith) many ſoules, in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther may be ſaid many truthes, as in glaſſes appereth many images of one face. Here thou maiſt well perceue, by ſaint auſten, that although ther may be ſaid many truthes, and that by reaſon, of the diuerſite of thingꝭ wherin it is, yet ther is but one trewth for all that. For doeſt thou not knowe, that as one thinge maie haue diuerſe and ſondry names, ſo maie diuerſe and ſondry thinges haue one name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>As how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Breade, drinke, fire, water, &amp;c. are eache but one thing, and yet hath eyther of them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſo manny ſondry names, as ther be ſondry langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherin thei are vſed to be ſpoken of neuertheleſſe the
<pb facs="tcp:3752:22"/>
diuerſitee of the names, doth not chaunge the vnitee or ſimplicitee of the thing, nor the vnitee or ſimplicitee of the thing, the diuerſitee of the names. And againe of the other ſide, thou maiſt eaſly finde ſome wher (as in ſome towne or pariſhe) twentie men of one name, yet the vnitee of the name, doeth not chaunge the diuerſitee of the perſons, nor the diuerſitee of the perſons, the vnitee the name. And euen ſo is it likewiſe (as I tolde the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) betwene the vnitee or ſimplicite of trewth, and the diuerſite of thinges wherin it is. For as the ſimplicite of trewth, doth not alter or change, the diuerſite of thinges, wherin it is. So the diuerſite of thingꝭ, doth not alter or chaunge, the ſimpliſite of the truth which is in them. Therfore truth in how many thingꝭ ſo euer it be, is yet (as ſaint Auſten ſaith) but one, al though of the commune ſort (for the cauſes afore ſaid) it be otherwiſe taken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>yea but yet, that commune ſort, doth ſo take it, as the ſcripture ſpeaketh it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, thou maiſt ſay this, that the ſcripture ſpeaketh it, euen as they do take it. for that the ſcripture doth ſo ſpeake it, is not the cauſe why, they ſo take it, but that they ſo take it, is the cauſe why the ſcripture doth ſo ſpeake it. for to whom (ſaieſt thou) dothe the ſcripture ſpeake it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>To whom but to men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore euen after the commune ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and capacite of menne it ſpeaketh it, And none other wiſe. wherin it doth not there teache any pluralitee, nor yet ſingularite, for it dothe but ſhowe after the maner of mens ſpeaking, what ſtate the children of men are in. And proueth nothinge els. wherfore this text, maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for thy purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3752:22"/>
               <head>Cap. 19.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir will ye geue me leue to talke my minde a while?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Spare not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, if there be (as you ſay) no more, no leſſe, nor none other, but euen the very ſame one ſingle and ſimple trewth, not onely in all and euery ſingular article of the faith, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in all and euery other thing and thinges, what ſo euer they bee beſide, this muſte iuſtly folowe, that who ſo euer denieth the trewth of any one thing, whether it be of the fayth, or not of the faith, denieth therin no leſſe then the trewth of all and euery thing that is. For when you wil haue it nedes followe, that he whiche denieth the trewth of any one article of the fayth, denieth therin the trewth of all the whole, becauſe there is (ye ſaie) no more, no leſſe, nor none other trewth in all the whole, then there is in eache and euery parte thereof. It muſte nedes folow likewiſe, that he whiche denieth the trewth of any other maner of thinge, denyeth therin the trewthe, bothe of all the fayth, and alſo of all other thinges what ſo euer they be beſide. Wherfore ſithe there is no man an heretike, but be cauſe he denieth the trewth of ſome part of the faith. And ageyne becauſe the very ſame trewthe whiche he denieth (if it be as you ſay) is in all and euery other thing beſide: it muſte alſo neds folowe, that who ſo euer denyeth the trewthe of any other thing, is alſo an heretike euen lykewiſe, as well as he, becauſe he denyeth no more, no leſſe, nor none other, but euen the verie ſame trewth, whiche the heretike dooeth denie. And yet farder, becauſe there is all moſte no man, but ſome tyme he denieth the trewthe of one thynge or an other. Wherin, becauſe they dooe all denie (by your ſayenge) none other but euen
<pb facs="tcp:3752:23"/>
alſo the ſame trewth, which an heretike doth denie, howe can this be auoided, but that all other men bee heretikes lykewiſe, euen as well as he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And doeſt thou beleue that to be trewe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ſyr, nor no man els I thinke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Marie this, by the manifeſte falſitee of this concluſion, I doe perceiue the falſitee of the poſicion, wherof it foloweth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Whiche is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen this that ye ſey, trewthe is no more, no leſſe, nor none other, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſingular thynge by it ſelfe, then it is in theim all, euen hole to gether: whiche (as ye maie nowe ſee) can not be trewe:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Arte thou at that poynte ageyn nowe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>who can be otherwiſe, when it dooeth here ſo plainly appere?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 20.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe ſo euer thou makeſt it appere to thy ſelfe, yet it appereth not ſo, to any man els, that foloweth reaſon: for did not I tell the before, that trewth, whiche is but one, and not diuerſe, doothe yet diuerſely behahaue it ſelfe in diuerſe thynges? As I declared vnto the, ſo farre as the caſe did then require?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What of that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall tell the what: becauſe I ſee the herein, ſo curious and inſaciable, that thou le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt nothynge vnſought (ſo farre as thy wit will ſerue the) which maie ſeme to make for thy purpos, thou ſhalte yet vnderſtande this muche farder, that all maner of thynges (Wherin the trewthe is (as aforeſaide) maie be deuided, in to theſe three ſundrie ſortes, that is to wit, one contingent and caſuall: an other more certayne and naturall: And the thirde diuine and ſpirituall. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in theſe three ſortes, the trewthe behaueth it ſelfe ſo diuerſely, that in thynges contingent and caſuall, it maie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3752:23"/>
be denied, without any danger or perill at all: as if thou and I ſhulde nowe contende, whether the turke be at Conſtantinople or no: if thou ſey ye, and I naie, or I ye, and thou naie, the one of vs bothe, denieth the trewthe playne. Alſo if thou ſeie the price of graine will not fall, but riſe before the yere come aboute: And I ſeie of the other ſide, that it will not riſe but fall: if it doe either the one or the other, the one of vs bothe denieth the trewthe lykewiſe: And ſo in all other thynges of that ſorte, what ſo euer thei be: yet what parell, hurte or daungier canſt thou fynde herin? when trewthe in this kynde of thyngꝭ, behaueth it ſelfe to all men (for diuers cauſes) ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, that thei maie therin graunte or denie, accordyng to their opinions, and yet not offende therin. Ageine, in thynges whiche are more certeine &amp; naturall, the trewth of as many as are vnknowne, leueth it ſelfe to the ſame libertee of iudgement, as it dothe in thynges contingent and caſuall: but of the reſte, whiche be manifeſte and well knowne, the trewthe can not be denied, of ſuche as dothe knowe them: as by exaumple, who can denie the fyre to be hote? no man I thinke, excepte he were out of his wit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes ſyr, for a man maie denie the fyre to be hote, if he will, although he knowe the trewthe of it neuer ſo well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>If he wolde ſo doe: what faute were that ſeieſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Suche and the ſame faute, as is the deniall of trewthe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>yea in that thynge thou maiſte ſaie, and in ſuche other lyke: but not as it is in euery thynge beſyde. For the deniall of trewthe in ſome thynges, is (as I doubte not, but thou wilt confeſſe) no leſſe then a damnable faute.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is trewe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And dooeſt thou thinke it a damnable faute, to denie the fyre to be hote?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3752:24"/>No not ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet thou thinkeſt it a more faute, then to denie the trewthe of what price, corne ſhall be the nexte yere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſte nedes thinke ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And whie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe this deniall is of a thyng certaine, manifeſt, and directely ageyn the perfite know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of the deniar: where as the other is but of a thynge incertaine, contingent, caſuall, and to the deniar but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecturall: wherfore it can not be ſuche a faute, to denie that I knowe but coniecturally, as it is to denie that I knowe moſte perfectely, as I knowe the fire to be hotte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, to denie the fyre to be hotte, is worthy more blame, then the other is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>It muſt nedes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet thou ſeiſt it is not damnable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore ſith it maie this apere, that trewthe bindeth not lyke nor ſo, in all thynges, but that (as thou doeſt graunt thy ſelfe) the deniall therof, in ſome thynge is damnable, and in ſome thynges not. And clere it is, that the damnable daunger and dammage therof, conſiſteth not in thynges contigent and caſuall: nor yet in thynges more certain and natural, but only in thinges concernyng our feithe, whiche are diuine and ſpirituall, how clerely maketh it ageinſt this that thou ſeieſt, who ſo euer denieth the trewthe of any maner of thynge, is as well an heretike as he is, whiche denieth the trewthe of any article of the feithe, becauſe the one denieth no more, no leſſe, nor none other, but euen the ſame trewth, whiche the other dothe? This (thou maieſt perceiue) can not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. For it is not the deniall of trewthe onely, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an heretike: but it is the deniall therof, in ſuche or ſuche a thynge, and that of our feithe onely, and not in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery or any other thynge beſide our feithe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3752:24"/>
               <head>Cap. 21.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr I ſeid not as ye take it, but I ſeid this, that ſo it muſte nedes folowe of this your ſeyng, that there is no more, no leſſe, nor none other trewth in any one thyng, then there is in any other, or in the whole multitude of thynges all together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I wolde graunt as muche, and the ſame my ſelfe, if trewth beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it ſelfe in euery thynge a lyke, as thou diddeſt thinke, and take it at the firſte: but nowe becauſe thou maieſt right well perceiue, howe muche thou wer therin decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: the trewth therfore beyng (as I ſaide) but euen one in all thynges, dooeth yet behaue it ſelfe ſo in tharticles of the feithe, that the deniyng therof in any one of them, maketh no leſſe than an heretike in dede. And further ageyne, after an other ſorte, it behaueth it ſelfe ſo, in ſuch certaine and naturall thynges, as be apparent and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the deniynge therof in ſome of them, maketh a wilfull and a we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>warde foole, but yet no heretike for all that: becauſe there is in it no perell of damnacion. And finally, it behaueth it ſelfe ſo, in thinges contingent and caſuall, that the deniyng therof in them, maketh lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or no faute at all: and this diuerſe behauiour of truth in diuers thynges, is not without reaſon, and good cauſe whie. For in the firſte caſe, it committeth it ſelfe, onely to the perpetuall helthe and welthe of mannes ſowle. In the ſeconde caſe, to the temporall neceſſite of this lyfe, and exerciſe of mannes witte and reaſon. And in the thirde and laſte caſe, onely to the libertee of mannes opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: In whiche three, the deniall therof, can not be of one degre but of diuers. And therfore, of ſo farre vnlyke parell and ieoperdie, as there is difference betwene eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion, &amp; in ſome caſe no penaltee, wherfore it is
<pb facs="tcp:3752:25"/>
plaine, that the deniall of trewth, is not hereticall, but wherin it behaueth it ſelfe, only to the helth and welth of mans ſoule, and that is not in thinges (as I ſayd) contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and caſuall. Nor yet in thinges of any cource natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but onely in thinges theologicall, that is to ſaie, in thinges diuine and ſpirituall. Now therfore, tell me where are all thy ſore obiections be cum, which thou haſt hitherto made, ageinſt the pure inuinſible vnite and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſitee of trewth? wherin thou haſt cauſed, a much more waſt of time thou neded by a great deale. And al to excuſe colour, and hide the moſt miſerable ſtat of an heretike, which, when thou haſt all done, will yet appere, and aſke the no leue. For when the articles of the feith, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and many, And the trewth of them all but one (as thou maiſt now perceue thy ſelfe) how can this be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but he that denieth the ſame one, denieth the trewth of them all together? when they, both eache and all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, haue no more, no leſſe, nor none other, but euen the ſame one, as it is declared and proued vnto the before. For els, how commeth it thus to paſſe, that the deniall of one article, ſhuld purchaſe damnacion, rather then the graunt and confeſſion of all the reſte, ſhulde purchaſe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacton? It ſemeth much more reaſon, that the graunte and confeſſion of many, ſhulde be more able to helpe and ſuccoure, then the deniall of one, ſhuld hurte and hinder, being (as they are) of like and equall power. yet becauſe in this cace, it is farre otherwiſe then ſo, tel me why doth one denied, leſe more, then all the other graunted, can get or ſaue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I wolde knowe that of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Trewly there is none other whie, but onely becauſe the trewth of them all, is perfite and whole in the ſame one, which is denied. And therfore the reſt can not helpe, in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3752:25"/>
whom, there whole and onely trewth is ſo refuſed. and to this it maie well be applied,<note place="margin">1 Corin. 5.</note> whiche tholy apoſtle Saint Paule doth ſay, <hi>Modicum fermentum to tam maſſam corrumpit,</hi> that is to ſaie, a litle leuen chaungeth the taſt of the whole lumpe of dow. wherof hath riſen (as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) this olde, and very trewe prouerbe, one vice deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth many vertues. And why ſo few as one? but onely becauſe, the perfection and vnitee of trewth, (which is not onely, in all vertues whole together, but alſo in each and euery one vertue by it ſelfe alone) is refuſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned in the committing of any one mortall vice, that chaunceth to fall in man. And therfore becauſe in vices, there is multiplicitee of errour, and contrariwiſe in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, very ſimplicitee of trewth, when ſo euer any one vertue is contemned, all the reſt can not helpe, becauſe in that one, ther whole perfection and indiuiſible trewth, is cleane deſpiſed. This the holy ſcripture dothe well confirme, which doth ſaie,<note place="margin">Iaco. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Quicum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> totam legem ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauerit, offendat autem in vno factus eſt omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reus,</hi> that is to ſay, who ſo euer doth kepe the whole lawe, and offendeth but in one parte, he is yet made giltie of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Now therfore content thy ſelfe with enough, and take this for an infallible trewth (as I tolde the before, and now is ſufficiently proued) that who ſo euer denieth any parte of the faith, denieth therin the trewth of all the whole. And who ſo euer denieth the trewth of all the whole feith, denieth the trewth of Chriſt. And who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer denieth the trewth of Chriſt, denieth him. And who ſo euer denieth him, denieth God him ſelfe. And this (as I ſaid) doth euery heretike without faile. Wherfore now, iudge thou thy ſelfe, in what cace they leade their liues.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:26"/>
               <head>Cap. 22.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir herin I muſt nedes make with you a greate ſtaie before we paſſe any farder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What yet ageyn?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>yea trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe the Turkes and diuerſe other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, deny Chriſt, and yet they deny not god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thinkeſt thou ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye and ſo doth euery man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAT.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not trewe, for ſo do not I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>why?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I know the contrary, for this can not be auoyded, but who ſo euer denieth Chriſt to be the ſame that he is, denieth him vtterly. And moſte trewe it is, that he is very god, wherfore who ſo euer denieth him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth god. And euen ſo doth the turkes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then how commeth it to paſſe, that they do otherwiſe thinke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſpeakeſt thou here, of a turkiſh thinking, while we be in matters of our faith whiche they refuſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir I ſpeake it not but becauſe it ſemeth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry repugnant to this your ſaying, that who ſo euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth Chriſt denieth God, when the Turkes doeth the one, but not the other, ſo farre as I perceue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>ye there thou ſaieſt well, ſo farre as thou perceueſt. But I and many other, perceue more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That more, wolde I faine here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then thou muſte well marke and conſider this, that this worde Chriſt, doth not properly ſingnifie, his onely humanite, nor yet his onely diuinitee ſeuerally or perticularly. But it ſignifieth indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidually and indiſtinctly one proper and ſingular perſon made of them both, like as this word, Iohn or Thomas, ſignifieth properly, nother the fleſh, nor yet the ſoule per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly. But the very vnitee and ſingularitee of the perſon made of them both together, although it be ſome tyme otherwiſe vſed, or rather abuſed, by reaſon of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3752:26"/>
a certayne maner of ſpeache, which ſignifieth ſomtyme the whole by the name of a parte, and contrariwiſe, ſome tyme a parte by the name of the whole, but yet neuer ſo taken properly. And therefore as he, whiche denieth that ſame perſon, whiche is properly ſignified by this worde Iohn or Thomas, denieth not onely the fleſhe, but alſo the ſoule, nor only the ſoule, but alſo the fleſhe, and that for the very vnitee of perſon, wherin they ar knitte, made, and be come both one (bothe one I ſey) not in, or for any confuſion, mutation, or alteration of ther propre natures or ſubſtance, but in and for, the very ſingularite and pure vnite of perſon. Euen ſo he whiche deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that ſame perſon, which is properly ſignified by this worde Chriſt, denieth not onely his very humanitee, but alſo his verie diuinitee, nor onely his very diuinitee, but alſo his very humanitee. And that for the propre vnitee of perſon, wherin they are knitte, made, and bee come both one, (bothe one I ſaie) not in, or for any confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, mutacion, or alteration of their propre natures, or ſubſtance, but in, and for the very propertee and vnitee of perſon. Wherfore, when the Turkes denie Chriſt, they deny both god and alſo the man. for Chriſt is none other but euen both together, and for that cauſe, the one can not be denied, with out the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes ſir, for they graunte Chriſt to be a very manne, but not very God.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 23.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAT.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I perceue, thou doſt not euen very wel, vnderſtand the matter. for it ſemeth by thy talke, that thou putteſt no difference, betwen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this name (Ieſus) &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this name Chriſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:3752:27"/>
one (beſide the high and miſticall interpretacion therof) ſignifieth nothyng els but only the man. And the other, nothyng els, but onely that perſone, whiche was made bothe of god and man. For of the name of Ieſus, there hath ben diuers: but of the name of Chriſte, properly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer but one acordyng to thexample therof taught &amp; geuen vnto vs, by thauctoritee of our holy mother the catholike churche: whiche exaumple ſhe daily ſingeth and ſeithe, as the reaſonable ſoule and the fleſh is one man: ſo god &amp; man is one Chriſte: wherfore, as he that graunteth me to be a bodie, and denieth my ſoule, or graunteth me to be a ſoule, and denieth my bodie, doth yet bothe waies denie me vtterly to be a veraie man, whiche conſiſteth onely in the compoſicion or copulacion of theim bothe to gether. Euen ſo he, that graunteth <hi>Ieſus</hi> of Nazareth to be a very man, &amp; denieth hym to be very god, or graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him to be very god, and denieth him to be very man, dooeth yet bothe the waies denie hym vtterly to be very Chriſte: whiche conſiſteth onely, in the compoſicion or copulacion (if I maie ſo call it) of them bothe together. And therfore, if thou haddeſt ſaide this, that the turkes grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth <hi>Ieſus</hi> of Nazareth to be a very man, but not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry god, thou hadſt ſemed to haue ſaid ſomwhat like to the purpos: but when thou ſeiſt thei graunt Chriſte to be a very man, but not very god, thou reporteſt them to doe, that is impoſſible. For it is no more poſſible, in this woorde Chriſte, to dooe the one without the other, then it is poſſible in this woorde man, to denie the ſoule with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fieſhe, or the fleſhe without the ſoule, whiche can neuer be done. For in this woorde man, the deniall of the one, doth alwaie included, the deniall of the other. For no fleſſhe no man, no ſoule no man, and lykwiſe in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3752:27"/>
Chriſte, no god, no Chriſte, no man, no Chriſte. And therfore I ſaie, as I ſaide, that all thoſe, whiche denie Chriſte, denieth god hym ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 24.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet me thinketh for all this, it dooeth not euen ſo fully folowe as ye make it for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I praie the tell me why.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe, although the Turkes denie god to bee in Chriſte, or in Ieſus of Nazareth, chooſe you whether. Yet for all that, it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not, that thei denie god. For it is two thynges to denie god, and to denie hym to be in this, or in that. And therfore when he is not denied to be the ſame that he is, clere it is, that he is not denied in dede. For a thynge can not be denied, excepte it be denied to be the ſame that it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but I ſey this, that they denie god to be the ſame that he is. For when thei denie hym to be ioyned in the vnitee of perſone with Ieſus of Nazareth, what do thei els, but euen denie Chriſt at the leaſt, whan they will none of that, whiche is Chriſte in dede? &amp; when they (as they doe) vtterlie denie Chriſte, what doe they els, but clerelie denie hym to bee the veraie ſame that he is? Therfore what is the ſame that he is? wilt thou, or any trewe chriſten man anſwere and ſey any other, but very god and man? wherfore, when he is bothe the one and the other, what thynge is it, that ioigneth them both ſo to gether, but euen the veray vnitee of perſon, whiche is proprely ſignified by this worde Chriſte? And therfore when thei denie Chriſte, what doe thei els, but clerely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie both? &amp; when thei denie both, may we not iuſtly ley to their charges, the very deniall of which we liſt? wherfore trew it is (as I ſaid before) that thei denie god for al this.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:28"/>
               <head>Cap. 25.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HHERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not ſaie ſo, for any thynge that I haue yet herde hitherto.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>what wilt thou ſaie then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſey this, that they denie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them bothe, that is to ſaie nother god nor the man nother, but onely any ſuche vnitee of perſon, as is made of them both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen as I might ſay, I nother denie thy ſowle nor yet thy bodie, but euen onely, any ſuche vnitee of perſon, as is made of them bothe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, what doe I denie, when I denie that but vtterly this, that thou art a man? For what is a man, but euen one whole complet perſon aduned and made of a bodie and a reaſonable ſowle? therfore, when I denie the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitee therof, I denie the whole complete perſon. And when I denie the whole complet perſon, whiche thou art what is by nature in the, that I denie not? for whan I denie in the, no leſſe then the whole: is there any parte of it lefte, that is vndenied? for the deniall of the whole, dooeth euer more clerely exclude thexcepcion of any parte or partes therof: wherfore when the deniall of the whole, doth alwaie include the deniall of all the partes. Clere it is, that the deniall of all the partes, muſt nedes folowe and be agreable to the deniall of the whole, wherupon it dependeth. Therfore when the deniall of the whole, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vtterly to the not beyng therof: the deniall of the partes which are included therin, muſt of neceſſitee tende to the ſame, that is to ſaie to the not beynge of them all lykewiſe: excepte thou wilt ſaie, that a man maie denie the whole tree: and denie not the barke or the bowes therof, or denie the whole apple, and denie not the coore or the kernell therof: wherfore herein thou makeſt but a mere cauilacion, nothyng to the purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3752:28"/>
               <head>Cap. 26.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I will not ſo geue it ouer: for ſuppoſe, that yeſterdaie, there died a man, whoſe bodie is yet vnburied: may not I therfore nowe, denie the vnitee of his perſon, who is clerely diſſolued and clene gone, and yet not therin denie his bodie nor his ſoule nother, which were the partes therof, &amp; now remaine a ſonder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes well enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than ſay you the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of the Turkes, whiche denie but onely the vnite of Chriſtes perſon, wherin ye ſaie they alſo denie both god and the man, whiche are the partes therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>So I ſey ſtill, and not without cauſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That cauſe wolde I faine here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then marke this, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall and thine in this caſe, doth include two contraries. For thy deniall ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth no farder then vpon the vnite of a perſon, whiche is diſſoliued dede &amp; gone. And therfore it muſt nedes be trewe: But their deniall runneth vpon the vnite of a perſon, which both is, &amp; euer ſhall be. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſte nedes be falſe. Alſo the partes of that which thou denieſt, are clene vntouched and not denied, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that thy deniall extendeth no farder, then to the not beyng of the vnite. wherof, although thei wer the partes, yet ſo they are not nowe. For they can not be the partes of that, whiche hath no beyng, and therefore in that they can not be denied. But the partes of that, whiche they denie, are denied in dede. Becauſe their deniall exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, nor to the not beynge, but to the very beyng of the vnitee, wherein and whereof they are nowe the partes and euer ſhall bee. And therfore thou muſte conſider, that it is two thynges to denie the beyng of that whiche is: and to denie the beynge of that whiche is not. Thou denieſt no more but the vnitee whiche is not. And they
<pb facs="tcp:3752:29"/>
denie the vnitee, whiche bothe is and euer ſhall be, which can not be denied (as I toulde the before) without the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniall of what ſo euer is conteined therin, And that is both god and man. And therfore thine example in this caſe will not ſerue, becauſe it is nothing lyke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet if all this, be as ye ſaie, I maruell why the turkes do not perceue it. for I thinke they be men of as great wittꝭ as we be, and haue amonge them learnyng alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAT:</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhuldeſt nothing maruell therat, if thou dideſt wel conſider, theſe wordꝭ, (after ſome tranſlacion) of the holy prophet Iſai,<note place="margin">Iſai. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Niſi credideritis, non intelligetis,</hi> that is to ſay, Except ye beleue, ye ſhall not vnderſtand. Wherfore, their infidelitee is the cauſe of their blindnes, which is ſuche and ſo great, as driueth them, to graunt the ſame, that they deny, &amp; to deny the ſame that they graunt. And yet ſee it not nother, as the ſame holy prophet doeth ſay,<note place="margin">Iſai. 6.</note> they ſee and ſee not, they here and vnderſtande not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but how dooe they graunte the ſame they denie. And denie the ſame they graunte?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue tolde the ſo much alredy, if thou be remembred: For when they graunte Ieſus of Nazareth to be but a very man and no more, they denie the ſame ageine, when they denie Chriſt, becauſe Chriſt is not only the ſame but alſo imcomparable more. Ageyn when they graunt god to be very god, and no leſſe, they denie the ſame agein, when they denie Chriſt, becauſe Chriſt is the very ſame, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo muche leſſe,<note place="margin">Iſai. 8.</note> as of him the prophet to god doth ſay, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuiſti eum paulominus ab angelis,</hi> That is to ſaie: thou haſt made him ſome what leſſe then angels. And therefore when in him they denie, both the more, whiche is god, and alſo the leſſe which is man, what dooe they els, but of both ſides, denie in dede, the verie ſame, which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3752:29"/>
they wene and ſeme to graunt, that is to ſay, euen all to gether. Wherfore let this be ſufficient (as it is in dede) to repell thy great ſtay, made agein this that I ſayd before, whoſoeuer denieth Chriſt, denieth god, which ſaieng is moſt trew, as it is now ſufficiently proued. And therfore who ſo euer denieth god, although he do it not with his tong, yet at the leaſt he doth it in his hart. And ſo with out faile doth euery heretike, in whom, (as I ſayd before) theſe wordes of the prophet, the folyſhe man ſayd in his hart, there is no god, are well and iuſtly verified.<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou haſt now, by this much, a farder occaſion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou maiſt the better perceue and ſee, what maner of ſtate it is, wherin euery heretike leadeth his life.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 27.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet ſir when ye haue all doone, becauſe the effect of your concluſion is this, that there is no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retyke, but he denieth the trewth of all the whole faith, and therfore of Chriſt and god hym ſelfe alſo. How ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I pray you) maie this agree with all, (which is not vnknowne) that all heretikes doth both holde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, diuerſe and many articles of the faith, as erneſtly, and as vehemently as any other man can, ſeyng and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thinking them ſelues, as verely to beleue them, as any men dooe, yea and wolde ſuffre death therin, rather then denie them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Suffer death? nay ſofte, therin thou goeſt to farre, for thou art not able to defende that ſeying, by any authenticall writing, reaſon, or example.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes ſir by example, for ye can not denie your ſelfe, but many haue willingly ſuffered death, for the trewth of diuerſe poyntes of the feyth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but what many were thoſe I pray the? any heretikes
<pb facs="tcp:3752:30"/>
troweſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>why not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly, for is there any deth ſo pretious and profitable, that maie come to man, as to die for the trewth of any parte of the faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore when it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuffer deth for that cauſe, is it to be thought to cum of the man him ſelfe, or els of the great grace and gift of god?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>when all that is good, cummeth of god, that muſt nedes be aſcribed vnto him alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſayeſt wel therin,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> And therfore: when this is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Preſioſa in conſpectu domini, mors ſanctorum eiꝰ,</hi> that is to ſaie, in the ſight of god precious is the death of his ſainctes. And when no deth amonge them is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as to dy for the trewth of the faith (in ſo much, that the gifte therof, is not geuen to all thoſe, whiche holdeth the trewth of the whole faith, nor yet, but to fewe of them nother in compariſon) wilt thou thinke, that euer any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, which hath directly forſaken (at the leaſte) ſome parte of the faithe, other dyd or ſhall obteyne that gifte? ſithe ſo many of them goeth with out it, whiche cleueth to the whole fayth all together. Beſide this, wh eneue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heretyke, whiche forſaketh directly (as I ſaied) ſome parte of the ſaythe, doth it freely, of his owne wilfull mynde, with out any coaction or compulſion at all. will any man thinke, that he wolde ſticke at the deniall of any other parte therof, if he were conſtrayned vnto it, with no leſſe then the feare and payne of death? Special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when tholy goſpell doth ſaie <hi>Qui in modico iniquus eſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>et in maiori iniquus eſt,</hi> he that is (he ſeyeth) vniuſt in litle, is alſo vniuſte in more? for he that wolde denie the, of one grote of thy duetie, with out any prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of nede, I thynke wolde not ſtycke, ſoone to denie the of twentie, yf he felt any neede pricke hym ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3752:30"/>
unto. Therfore, neuer ſai or thinke that an heretik, which hath with out compultion, forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and directly denied, ſome parte of the fayth all redy, wold ſuffre deth, for any other parte therof, when the moſt part of thoſe (as I ſeid) which hath &amp; holdeth the whole faith altogether, ſhall not reach or attene to that gift of moſt precious deth, which is not geuen (as I ſaid) but to few in compariſon. And yet thoſe, in whom ther is the confeſſion of the whole fayth, (thou maiſt wel know) muſt nedes be nere it, then thoſe, in whom there is the deniall of parte. extepte thou wilte make betwene them this difference, that in the one there is ſome poſſibilite thereof, and in the other none at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>why ſir, yet I haue harde ſay, that there haue bene diuerſe heretikes, whiche hath ſuffered death for ſome parte of the fayth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſay you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In very dede as a thefe, when he is hanged, doeth ſuffre deathe, for ſome parte of the commune welth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That is a proper ſimilitude.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt meete for the purpoſe that I can finde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſir, a theefe is not hanged, but for that he doeth ſteale</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATHO.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou arte therein dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. for if he ſteale, money, horſe, kyne, ſheepe, or ſuche other lyke, becauſe his lyfe is muche better then any of thoſe thinges, it were therfore no Iuſtice nor equitee, but rather very crudelitee to take his lyfe a way for any of them, when that puniſhmente ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth the value of that he ſtole. And therefore he is not hanged for any ſuche thinges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe he and all ſuche, are ſo iniurious and hurtfull to the commune welthe, that if they ſhulde lyue and continewe, it ſhulde by them, ſo decaie, and be trodden vnder the foote, that no manne
<pb facs="tcp:3752:31"/>
ſhulde be able to kepe that he hathe, and to liue one by an other, excepte it were ſuch as coulde and wolde, plaie (as they ſaie) catche that catche maie. And therfore thei be not hanged, but for the commune welthe. And yet not becauſe thei make with it, but becauſe thei make ſo ſore, and all that thei can directly ageinſt it. And euen ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I will not ſeie naie, but many heretikes haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered deathe for ſome parte of the feithe. Not becauſe thei helde with it, but becauſe they went from it, and held extremely ageinſt it. And muche more miſchiefe therin wolde haue done to it, if thei had not bene therin, by ſuch worthy dethe, preuented: And therfore any other dethe of an heretike, for the trewthe of the feyth then this, thou ſhalt neuer be able to proue.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 28.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr herein ye haue ſaide your conceite: but how ſey you to my queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Haue ye ſo ſoone forgotten, that vpon yur concluſion, that all heretikes dooeth denie the trewth of the whole feithe, I aſked you, how might that agree with this, that all they holde and manifeſtly confeſſe ſo many articles therof as thei doe? ſeiyng and alſo thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng them ſelfes therin as verely to beleue them, as any men can do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I maruell greatly that thou wilt haue (in this caſe) any maner of reſpecte to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng or thinkyng other, ageinſte ſo manifeſte &amp; inuincible reaſon as I haue therin ſhewed the. For in this, be thou nowe iudge thy ſelfe: doe they, other ſaie or thinke them ſelfes any more ſuer of the trewthe in any pointe, then thei ſaie and thinke thei bee ſuer in the very ſame, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thei doe directly erre in dede? howe erneſtly doe they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3752:31"/>
thynke, that thei be not therin deceiued? ſhall we thinke ſo to, becauſe of that? Thoſe whiche did murder and ſleie thappoſtles (as our ſauiour hym ſelfe did prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie) thought thei did therin great ſeruice to god.<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> But yet for all their thinkyng, was it as thei thought? or did their thinkyng excuſe their faute, becauſe thei thought it was none? Therfore why ſpeakeſt thou to me of an heretikes thinkyng? when it is not poſſible for hym to thinke that, which were of all thingꝭ moſt expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for him to thinke. That is to ſaie, that hym ſelfe is an heretike: what thyng might he thinke more trewly: and yet he is not able ſo to do. Therfore neuer let his ſeiyng or thinkyng, what ſo euer it be, ſtande in thy weie, betwene the and ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſon: wherof in this caſe thou haſte harde enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede I wolde not ſo muche paſſe vpon that, as I dooe: if it were not more for other mens thinkyng, then for theirs, whiche are no heretikes in dede. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, yea and that the moſte parte, dooeth vtterly beleue and thinke, that no heretike doth denie the trewthe of the whole feithe, nor yet any more of it nother, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen onely of thos poyntes, wherin he doth directly erre, and differ from other faithfull people.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray the who be they that ſo thinke? any other but ſuche as are not able to diſcerne and vnderſtande the thynge? or any other but ſuche, as iudgeth more by coniecture, then by any dewe order of reaſon, wherof little ſkyll they can? farre a ſonder it is, to iudge thynges as they ſeme, and to iudge them, as thei bee in dede: whiche very fewe in reſpecte can doe: ſpecially when the matters be ſomwhat darke, as they be in this caſe. And therfore, what is the iudgement or opinion of ſuche, to be pondered herein?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:32"/>
               <head>Cap. 29.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr wyll ye beleue me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>In very dede, I my ſelfe can not yet thinke, that an heretike doth denie the trewth of thoſe articles, whiche he doth ſo manifeſtly graunt and confeſſe. And more ouer vtterly beleue and thinke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as he ſaithe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What not yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Than we muſt haue a farder talke, then I thought we ſhulde nede. For nowe I wot what thou doeſt lacke herein well enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doeſt not conſider (I perceiue) any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitee of denials: but as though there were no mo but euen bare one, when there is one directe, whiche is ſo comune and alſo playne, as can gender do doubte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And an other, indirecte or conſequent, which is more obſcure darke and ſecrete. and therfore not ſo eaſie to be perceiued. By reaſon wherof, a thynge maie ſometyme ſeme to be graunted, when it is neuer the leſſe denied: as it is nowe in this caſe. And more plainly doth apere, in that I ſaid vnto the before of the Turkes: who (as thou ſaieſt) doth graunt god, but how? none otherwiſe but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, deniyng the ſame ageyn conſequently: as thei do, when thei denie Chriſt, whiche maketh their graunt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng worth. For a directe grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, can neuer ſtande with a conſequent denial, which plucketh awai the trewth and perfection, of what ſo euer is graunted before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought all this while, that there was ſome ſubtiltee in this deniall, whiche ye haue ſo longe ſpoken of, or els it were not poſſible, for that ye haue ſaid to be trew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou call y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which is very conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but a ſubtilte, thou ſhalt yet finde it a ſubtiltee of ſuch a ſorte, as wherin, all heretikes deceiue not onely them ſelfes, but alſo as many
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3752:32"/>
as folow them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That deceite maketh but a ſmall faute, ſo longe as their deniall renneth not agayne the thynge directely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>So thou woldeſt haue it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: but thou ſhalte finde it farre otherwiſe for all that: wherfore, although it will make ſome digreſſion before we come to the very ſolucion of thy queſtion, yet to ſee the trewthe hereof, wilt thou call that but a ſmall faute, whiche the holy prophet dooeth note in hym, that ſeith in his herte, there is no god?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No mary ſyr,<note place="margin">Pſal 13.</note> for I thynke there can be no greatter faute then that, becauſe he that ſo dooeth denieth hym directly, and not conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATHOLI.</speaker>
                  <p>howe knoweſt thou that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Uery well. for he that ſeithe in his herte there is no god, can neuer denie a thynge more directly, then he denieth that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou ſay ſo, tell me howe doth he, ſaie that in his herte?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſaith it, with the worde of his thought, which is conceued within, although it come not out with the voice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that worde of his thought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſo euer he thinketh to be ſo or not ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>How many ſhall we finde, that doth with that woorde, euen ſey in the herte, there is no god?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt how many ſo euer there be, that ſo ſeith in the herte, I thinke there be none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that dare &amp; will ſo ſaie with his mowth, or yet ſo writ with his pen. And therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worde of thought alone, is not open, but only to him, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is: how ſhuld we finde any ſuch, although there were many, as I thinke there be not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Dooeſt thou not thinke there be many of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe the prophet ſpeaketh it, but of one perſon ſingularly. For he doth not ſey, (the foliſhe men) but the foliſhe man ſaide in his herte, there is no god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou maieſt
<pb facs="tcp:3752:33"/>
not take it ſo, for the prophet perceuing a multitude wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in this horrible and abhominable blindneſſe, doth here touch and open the venemous curſidnes of all the whole ſort, in the perſon of one of them, as it may well appere by his owne wordꝭ immediately folowing, whiche are theſe. <hi>Corrupti ſunt et abhominabiles facti ſunt in ſtudiis ſuis.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal 13.</note> They are (he ſaith) corrupted, and become abhominable in ther fancis. This he ſaieth (as thou hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt) not of one, but of many, That is to wit, of the whole ſort, whoſe moſt peſtilent wickednes, he towcheth before, (as I ſayd) in the perſon of one of them. Wherfore thou maiſt not take it, that he meaneth it of one perſon alone, or of few mo, but in dede of very many. And now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the purpoſe ageine, whether this foliſh fellow, which denieth god in his hart, denieth him directly or no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no doubt of that, as I ſhowed you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but yet thou muſte make me a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proffe therof then ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then my proffe ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be this, when he ſaieth in his hert, there is no god, and the ſame ſayeng in his hert, is none other, but in his hert ſo to thinke, And becauſe no man can thinke any thinge in his hert to be ſo, or not ſo, but euen directly, it muſte nedes followe, that this foliſh felowe in his hert denieth god directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That foloweth not, for where thou ſayeſt, that no man can thinke in his herte, any thing to be ſo, or not ſo, but euen directly, that I deny. For it is not trewe, except thou adde vnto it this condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if he be ware of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, is it poſſible for any man to thinke, that he him ſelfe is not ware of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>why not, as well as to ſpeake, that he hym ſelfe is not ware of? for haſt thou not ſome tyme harde this report of a man, that he ſpake he wiſt nere what? and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3752:33"/>
yet neither madde, dronke, nor an Ideot nother, And why therfore, maie not a man thinke, he wot nere what as wel as ſo to ſpeake? when ſo ſpeaking can not procede but of ſo thinking?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>yea but yet, when a man doeth ſo ſpeake, it is not ſaide he ſpeaketh he wot nere what, becauſe he is not ware what he ſayth, but becauſe he is not ware what of neceſſitee foloweth of his ſeying. For of his ſaying it ſelfe, he is ware what it is well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, or els he coulde not repete the ſame againe, which ye knowe he can do, although he be not ware what muſt folowe therof: for that is it, for the whiche it is ſaide, he ſpeaketh he wotteth nere what, and for nothinge els.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it ſo be. And yet, what ſo euer doth ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that ſame both is, and muſt nedes be, conteyned in his ſaying, or els it coulde by no meanes folow therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That I graunt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then take euen the ſame of his thinking, becauſe the reaſon and trewth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is all one, for as he is ware of his ſaying directly, and yet is ignorant and vnware therof conſequently, That is to wit, as he woteth what he ſayth, and woteth not what dothe folow therof, which is conteyned therin, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo it is of his thinking likewiſe. for both ſaying and thinkinge haue in them commonly, a duble vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, one direct, and on other conſequent. And therfore when the name or reporte of ſaying or thinking, proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and is taken very ofte, as well of that vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which is but conſequent, as of that whiche is direct, what haſt thou more to proue, that this foliſhe fellowe which ſaieth in his hart ther is no god, denieth him in his hart directly, rather then conſequently? for all this that thou haſte hitherto ſeyde will not ſerue.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:34"/>
               <head>Cap. 30.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue this of the prophet to proue it by, that he ſeyth in his hart, ther is no god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>ye but yet, when this ſame ſaying in his hart, is (as afore ſayd) the very thynking in his mynd, and the ſame thinking hauinge in it as it hathe, not onley a directe ſence, but alſo a conſequente, whether dothe the prophette meane it of the directe ſence, or els of the ſence conſequete? for therin dothe lie all the doubt: becauſe the ſaying of the prophette behaueth it ſelfe indifferentlie vnto them both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr the prophet muſte nedes meane it of the direct ſence of his thinkynge onely, as it may well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere by theſe wordes, which he ſpeaketh alſo of hym, ſo playnly in an other place, ſeying, <hi>Non eſt deus incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu eius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> There is (he ſayth no god in his ſight. And becauſe the prophet doth here not meane the ſight of the outward eye of the bodie, but the ſight of the inwarde eye of the mynde, wherby, a man dothe directly thinke, what ſo euer he taketh to be ſo, or not ſo, it muſt nedes followe that the prophet meaneth it of that ſence of his thinking, wherin he thinketh directly, what ſo euer he dothe thinke. For if he hadde in that ſence of his thinkinge, that there were a god: doubtleſſe the prophette wolde not haue ſayde of hym this, that there is no god in his ſight, whiche is as much to ſay, as there is no god in his meaning, or ſo farre as he doth directly thinke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore clere it is, that he denieth god in his hart directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATHO.</speaker>
                  <p>That foloweth not, for thou muſte conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what the prophette ſaythe alſo of hym, but a litle after in the ſame pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> which thou doeſt allege, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his wordes be theſe, <hi>Dixit in corde ſuo oblitus eſt deus, auertit fuciam ſuam ne videat in finem,</hi> that is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3752:34"/>
to ſay, he ſayde in his hart, god hath for gotten, he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth away his face, and will neuer ſee it. Alſo a litle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, the prophet inueieth farder againſt him, with this queſtion, <hi>Propter quid irritauit impius deum? dixit enim in corde ſuo non requiret,</hi> whiche is this muche to ſay, why dothe the taityfe attempt or prouoke god? for he ſayth in his hart, he will not looke vpon it. Now by theſe wordes of the prophet, thou maiſte perceue ageyne, that he meaneth it not of this felowes deniall in his herte directly, but of his deniall conſequentlie. for if the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe fellowe hadde thoughte in his herte there hadde bene no god directly in deede, hee wolde not haue ſaide in his hart, that god hath forgotten, and that he turneth awaie his face and will neuer looke vpon it. For that which is not, can do none of all thoſe thinges or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyke. Therfore he did not ſaie in his hart directly, ther is no god, but yet he ſaide it conſequently, that is to ſaie, he conceiued (as euery heretyke doeth) ſuche thingꝭ in his hart directlie, wherof it muſte nedes folowe, that there is no god conſequentlie. Wherfore, ſo doth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet meane, and none otherwiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr herein ye be deceued, for this is not that fooliſhe fellow, which the prophette ſpake of before. But in very deede, it is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it appereth plaine by the prophetꝭ wordꝭ, whiche doth clerely ſhow, that the one doth ſay in his hart, there is no god, and the other the contrary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not trew, for the contrary is to ſay in his harte, there is a god, but he ſayth not ſo, for in his harte he ſayeth no more but that god hath forgotten, and will neuer looke vpon it, which is as muthe to ſaie as this, that god is not iuſt. As he were not, if he wold other forget, or neuer looke vpon the puniſhemente of iniquitee.
<pb facs="tcp:3752:35"/>
And therfore the prophet doth ſay, there is no god in his ſight, becauſe he ſeeth no iuſtice in god: whereof (if there were none, as he iudgeth in his herte) it muſt nedes fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that there were no god in dede: as there is not in the conſequence of that he ſaithe in his herte. Wherfore this place of the prophet doth but expounde and declare the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſyr not ſo, for the conſequent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of god, is diſcribed in this place, whiche you do here nowe allege. And the directe deniall of god, in the other two places alleged before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it ſo be: I wyll not greatly ſticke with the therein, ſith the deſcripcions of them bothe be ſuche, as declareth the conſequent deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to be at the leaſt, as euill as the other is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That I denie againe. For the ſcripture: of as many as be of his ſorte, whiche ſaithe in his herte, there is no god, dooeth plainly ſaie, they are corrupte, and become abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in their fantaſies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then take this with all,<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> that of as many as be of his ſorte, in whoſe ſight (as the ſcripture doe ſaie) there is no god, it ſaith alſo, their waies are euer more,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> filthy, polluted, or corrupted: and what maketh any ſorte abhominable, but onely ſuche waies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but the ſcripture in bothe thoſe places, dooeth ſpeake onely of them, whiche denieth god directely, and not of them, whiche bee of his ſorte, that ſaith in his herte,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> god hath forgotten. &amp;c. And therin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth hym not, but conſequently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What if I graunte the ſame? yet thou muſt marke as well what it ſaith alſo of that ſorte, as of the other before, although they denie hym not (as thou ſaieſt) but conſequently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe be the wordes, <hi>Epurge domine deus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; exaltetur manus tua, ne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuiſcaris pauperum.</hi> O lorde god (he crieth) ariſe, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3752:35"/>
lyfte vp thy hande, and forget not the poore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What is this to them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>More (I maie tell the) then all that is alleged before, is to the other. For the prophet knowyng the curſed iniquitee of theſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth god but conſequently to be ſuche, and ſo muche more gretter then could be expreſſed with any direct, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or ſpeciall wordes, was compelled to declare it, with onely exclamacion ageine them to god, for lacke of any other ſufficient waie or meane to expreſſe it by.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, if the prophet ſo me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it agein them as ye ſaie, why doth he adde vnto it this, forget not the poore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe theſe are, to the poore, the greatteſt perill and peſtilent plage, that euer was or is poſſible to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them. In ſo muche, that if god wolde permitte and ſuffre them to continewe, thei wolde not faile, if it were poſſible to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>roy and deuoure them all:<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prophet doth exclame and crie vnto god, to lifte vp his hande to ouerthrowe theim, that the poore might eſcape their miſcheuous indeuor, and wicked purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>whiche poore are thei?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>The poore in lernyng, the poore in knowlage, vnderſtandyng, &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſpecially of diuine miſteries. The poore alſo in their owne conceite: the poore in ſpirite, of whom it is written, <hi>beati pauperes ſpiritu,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> bleſſed are the poore in ſpirite: ſo poore, as knowth nothyng of their own, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryng alwaie theſe woordes of thapoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>quid habes ꝙ non accepiſti</hi>? what haſt thou (he ſeith) that thou haſt not receiued? &amp; therfore ſo poore, as cauſeth them, neuer to ceſſe beggyng &amp; crauyng of god, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (thei know) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth all the whole helpe &amp; ſuccour of their pouerte: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, dwelleth ſuch a number, and ſo many, as moueth the holy prophet of veri pitee, to exclame (as I ſaid) and crie
<pb facs="tcp:3752:36"/>
vnto god, for their defence and deliuerance, (among all other) from theſe, moſt ſpecially, which denieth not god, but conſequently. For of the other, this poore, can muche better beware then thei can of theſe, for the ſecret beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of their miſchiefe, whiche is muche more open in the other, and therfore leſſe perelous. wherfore, thus it maie well apere, that to denie god but conſequently, is at the leaſt no leſſe euill then it is to denie him directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr I wyll omit, for a while, what ſo euer I haue more to ſaie herein to the coutrary. And in the meane tyme I wold yet be anſwered to this my queſtion, how it may be (as you ſaie it is) that an heretike doth denie the trewth of thoſe articles, whiche he doth ſo directly graunt &amp; confeſſe, ye and more ouer, vtterly beleue and thinke therin as he ſaith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>haſt thou not forgotten that yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No mary ſyr, for there hath ben nothynge hitherto that maketh more ageinſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pith of your purpos, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doth.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 31.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then for the ſolucion therof, thou canſt not ſaie naie, but nowe thou ſeeſt a manifeſte dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of theſe two denials, wherof the one is directe, and the other conſequent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>All that I perceiue well enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore if thou beare that well in minde, thou ſhalt ſe thy doubte therby, clene put awaie. For whan an heretike denieth the trewth of ſome parte of the faithe directely, and the ſame trewthe (as it is proued before) is no more, no leſſe, or none other in any parte therof or in all together, then it is in the ſame parte whiche he doth directely denie, this muſte nedes folowe, that he denieth the trewthe of all the reſte conſequently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr then for example, take thaſcencion, for one of the articles, whiche an heretike dothe directly graunte
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3752:36"/>
and confeſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Contente.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore when he doth graunt and confeſſe the aſſencion directely, ye wyll not denie but that he doth graunt and confeſſe the trewth therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>yea and yet the ſame trewth I ſay, he denieth conſequently for all that: becauſe he denieth it, in ſome other article directly, for els he were no heretike at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then he dooeth graunte and denie one thynge bothe at once.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, directly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe can that be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede very ſildom in a iuſt man, I maie ſaie to the.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>In whom then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In an heretyke veray com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the faithe be diuerſe and many: And the trewthe of them all, but one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>not nothyng, if thou conſider a difference betwene them, and the trewthe that is in them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherby ſhuld I conſider a difference betwene them, and the trewthe that is in them, when there is no article, that can be without trewth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet thou maieſt well conſider it by this, that if there were not a difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene euery article of the faithe, and the trewthe whiche is in eache of them, there ſhuld be other ſo many diuerſe trewthes, as there be articles, (which are many in dede) or els ſo fewe articles, as there be trewthes, which is but one. wherfore this well conſidered, it maie ſone appere how an heretike doth graunt and deny one thynge both at once. That is to ſaie, graunt it directly, and denie it conſequently, as he doth in what ſo euer article he doth graunt: &amp; that thou maiſt the better perceiue it, ſuppoſe an heretike, which grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth the paſſion of Chriſte, &amp; deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his reſurreccion, as ſome of them did in time paſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3752:37"/>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then when he graunteth the trewth of the paſſion directly, doth he not denie the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame trewth conſequently, in that he denieth it in the reſurrection directly? for when both thoſe articles (as al the reſt) haue but one very ſimple and ſingle trewthe, which is in each of them, how can the ſame trewthe bee denied in the one article directly, but that it muſte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be alſo denied, as well in the other conſequently? as in cace, if thou were now in diuerſe places at once, as the trewth is in diuerſe articles, how coulde I denie the, in this place to be a man, but that I muſt therin, denie the to be the ſame, as well in all other places, where ſo euer thou arte beſide? how be it, in this place directly, and by reaſon of that, in all other places, conſequently. For the direct deniall of a thing to be the ſame that it is, muſte nedes folowe the thing, wherſoeuer it be. For one thing denied and not denied both at once, in reſpect of it ſelfe, can neuer be. And therfore no more can trewth, whiche is but one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir yet as I do now perceue, in reſpect of the two ſondry articles wherin it is, it may bee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye but not in both directly, for thou muſt yet farder conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der that this direct denial, runneth not onely, to wher or wherin, but alſo to what the thing is, which is in, for it is two thingꝭ to denie wherin a thinge is, and to deny, what the thinge is, as if I denie thy ſoule to be in thy hand, yet it foloweth not, that I denie it to be in thy foote, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other member of thy body beſide, becauſe that deniall runneth not, but onely to where or wherin it is, but if I take occaſion of thy hand to denie thy ſoule whiche is in it. And therin deny it directly to be the ſame that it is (as euery heretike taketh occaſion of one article or other to deny the trewth that is in it, and therin denieth it to bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3752:37"/>
the ſame that it is) it muſt therfore nedes folowe, that I denie thy ſoule, where, or wherin ſo euer it be, that is to ſay, as well in thy foote as in thy hande, and in euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte of thy body alſo, becauſe that deniall renneth not only (as I ſayd) to where or wherin, but alſo directly to what thy ſoul is, whiche is as well in euery ſenſible parte of thy body, as in thy hand, and all one. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although it be not directly denied, but in that parte onely, wherin the occaſion therof is taken, yet is it alſo conſequetly denied, wher ſo euer it is beſide. Wherfore euen ſuche is an heretikes deniall of the trewth, in what parte of the fayth ſo euer he denieth it, for his deniall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not onely to where or wherin the trewth is, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo directly, to the trewth it felfe. For that ſame trewthe he houldeth directly to be no trewth at all, which onely maketh hym an heretike. And therfore that ſame only trewth, once directly denied, can not be but denied (as I ſayd) where, or wherin ſo euer it be. How be it, directly in that parte, wherin the occaſion therof is taken, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently in all and euery other parte wherin ſo euer it is beſide. Wherfore denied (as I ſaide) and not denied, in reſpect of it ſelfe, can not be defended or borne, by any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitee of thinges, in how many ſo euer it be. For it is not poſſible that one very ſimple thing, beinge in deede directly denied, ſhoulde or might, by any meanes, all that while, be of the ſame denier verified or vndenied. And therfore this it may apere, how an heretike dothe denie the trewth of thoſe articles, whiche he doth graunt, that is (as I ſayd) graunt them directly and denie them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:38"/>
               <head>Cap. 32.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then can I ſay (I may tell you) euen as much of the other ſyde, for when ye ſay, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the trewth of the paſſion conſequently, in that he deniethe the trewthe of the reſurrection directlie. By the ſame reaſon, I ſay that he graunteth the trewth of the reſurrection conſequently, in that he graunteth the trewth of the paſſion directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>That wil not follow, in hym ſpecially.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>why not in him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe he is an heretike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>why wil it not followe in an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, as well as in an other man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe, when an other man graunteth the trewth of the paſſion, or of any other parte of the faith directly, he graunteth therin the trewth of the reſurrection and alſo of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther articles conſequently, &amp; that not onely becauſe there is none other but the ſame trewth in the paſſion, that is in the reſurrection and in all the whole faithe thorowly, but alſo ſpecially, becauſe he denieth no parte of the faith directly: But when theretyke graunteth the trewth of the paſſion directlie, it can not ſo followe in hym, that he graunteth the trewth of the reſurrection conſequentlie, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe therin he denieth the ſame trewth directly, whiche doth reſiſte and exclude his conſequent graunte vtterly: and therfore thou maiſt not take the graunt of an heretike to be ſuch, as is the graunt of an other man, for they bee farre vnlyke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet then by your ſaying, ſith the trewth of the paſſion, and the trewth of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is but al one, that ſame one, doth he directlie graunt and denie both at once, which is playne contradiction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede it were no leſſe, if that ſame directe graunt, and direct deniall of the trewth, mette both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one article, as they do not. But now becauſe the di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3752:38"/>
graunte of the trewth is in one article. and the direct denial of the ſame in an other, therfore by that, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction is cleane put a way. And all by reaſon of the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite of the thingꝭ, wherin the trewth is ſo graunted and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nied. Neuertheleſſe, although the ſame direct deniall of the trewth, can not mete and ioyne together, with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect graunte thereof, in one article, yet in the ſame one truth of both tharticles, the direct deniall, crepeth ſo nere the direct graunt ſecretly, that it doth infect and poiſon it with the propre venem of it ſelfe conſequently for all that, and maketh the graunt of no efficacie, much like, as wher a wicked mother can not come hir ſelfe, ſhe ſendethe a doughter of hir owne, as euil or wors then ſhe: for a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect denial, is as a verie mother, of a deniall conſequent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>And euen ſo, is a direct graunte, of a graunte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 33.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is to be taken, where a direct denial, maketh no impediment: for therof riſeth to an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, the ſame ſpecial priuilege to him only dew and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenient, that what ſo euer he graunteth of the faith, as an other man doth directly, ther ſhall neuer growe and come vnto hym any profit therof finally. For the iuſte graunte of a thing directlie, doth neuer ſo much prfitte and ſet forwarde, as the deniall therof conſequentlie, doeth hurt hinder and plucke backeward: for if I graunt the to be an honeſt man directly. And after many wordꝭ thereof reherſed accordingly, yet if I ſaie thou vſeſte thy nighbours maliciouſly, &amp; cleane ageinſt charite: do I not therin deny thine honeſtee conſequently? what profit ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore doth my graunt therin directly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>But little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay none at all, if thou marke it well, for howe can the
<pb facs="tcp:3752:39"/>
profyte or perfection of a thynge abide, where the trewth of it is in dede denied? and therfore although there be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo many articles graunted directely, yet it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, excepte it be ſo prouided that none be denied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently: And that can neuer bee done iuſtly, ſo longe as any one of them is denied directly. For that is able to infecte them all (as I ſayde) with a deniall conſequently. Accordyng to the ſaiyng of ſaint Paule (before alleged) <hi>modicum fermentum totam maſſam corrumpit:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1 Cor. 5.</note> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leuen ſoureth the whole lumpe of dowe. Therfore (as thou maieſt nowe perceiue thy ſelfe) it can not folowe, that an heretike hath trewely in dede, any parte of the faithe, other becauſe he dothe directly confeſſe and thinke many articles therof to be trewe (for he doth no leſſe both ſaie and thinke of his owne faithe, wherin he is deceiued) Nor yet becauſe the more parte of trewe chriſten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, doth not thinke hym to erre in any more, then he doth directely denie. For farder then that (as I ſayde) littell do thei perceiue or conſider, becauſe of ſuche thyngꝭ, what muſt folowe, thei ſeldome loke after: For beyonde their ſenſes, fewe of them doth reache. And as for any ſecretes of nature, they are ſcant able to touche: What place therfore can their iudgement haue, in thynges ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall? Wherfore what ſo euer he or they dooe ſaie or thinke, or how ſo euer to any of them both, it dooeth ſeme and appere, take this neuer the leſſe for a ſuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that euery heretike (although it be a thyng to him ſelfe incredible) is yet for all that, no leſſe then out of the trewthe, of all the whole faithe throughly. That is to ſaie out of it in parte before men: and out of it all together before god: with whom euery thynge doth appere, not as it ſe=meth, but as it is in dede.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:3752:39"/>
               <head>Cap. 34.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet ſyr, if it appere before god, as it is in dede: then it appereth before hym, with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, that where as he denieth ſome parte directely, he denieth all the reſte but conſequently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou no more but a but of that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhuld I make of it els?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhuldeſt make of it this, that there is no difference betwene them at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What not betwene a directe deniall, and a deniall conſequent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then are they both one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunt the ſame before hym.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>And not before men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe men can not ſo come by them bothe, as god hath them before him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then if they be but one before god, and two diſtincte before men, other god, or men, doth take them otherwiſe then thei be in dede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No not ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes ſyr, for if thei be but one, they can not bee two: if they bee two, they can not bee ſo litle or fewe as one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Therin thou art deceiued. For that whiche is but one in ſome reſpecte, may be two in an other reſpecte well enough: as thy bodie and thy ſoule are but one, in reſpecte of thy perſon. And yet they are two in reſpecte, of their diſtinct and proper natures. And therfore lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, although a directe deniall, &amp; a deniall conſequent be two diſtinct before men, in reſpect of their knowlage. Yet thei come both to one before god in reſpecte of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, wherin there is nothyng conſequent, but all preſent,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then by that, he knoweth not all, that men doth knowe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Wilt thou ſaie ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſemeth no leſſe by your ſaiyng.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>If all thynges be preſent to hym, and nothynge
<pb facs="tcp:3752:40"/>
conſequent: howe can he knowe a conſequent, whan (if it be as you ſaie) there is no ſuche before hym, that is to wit in his knowlage. and yet in mens knowlage there is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Men doth knowe the ſucceſſion of daies, howe one foloweth an other. And how they can not, but paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the firſte, before they come to the next, as the ſondaie before mundaie, and mundaie before tweſdaie, and ſo forthe. Yet the daies do not ſo paſſe and ſuccede one after an other before god in his knowlage, as they do before men, and in their knowlage. For he doth not (as who ſaie) tary and looke after ſuche or ſuche a daie or tyme as men doe: but hath mundaie as ſoone as ſundaie, and tweſdaie as ſoone as mundaie, and ſo euen the laſte as ſone as the firſte, and all at once: And therfore what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion can bee of them before hym?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as I ſayde before of a conſequent: if there be no ſucceſſion of theim before hym, he dooeth not knowe, that they ſeccede and folowe one an other, whiche men doothe knowe, and ſo by this, he knoweth not all that men kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That foloweth not, for he doth moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knowe: that they ſuccede one an other in reſpecte of their naturall cowrce, and of mens knowlage and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng therof: but not in reſpecte of his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and infinite knowlage, wherin the laſte (as I ſayde) cometh not after the firſte, nor yet the firſte before the laſte: wherfore in reſpecte of that knowlage, the daies haue no ſucceſſion at all: And euen ſo in lyke maner, he knoweth a conſequent, to be in reſpecte of it ſelfe, as it is in the order of nature, and of mans vnderſtandyng and knowlage therof. but not in euery condicion ſo, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of his owne proper &amp; infinite knowlage, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all: wherin (as I ſaide) there is nothyng before nor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3752:40"/>
after, preceding nor folowyng, firſt nor laſt, but all thingꝭ together at once, euen very preſent and premanent: and therfore how is it poſſible for a directe denial, &amp; a deniall conſequent, to haue any difference betwene them there? ſith there is no difference betwene them here but onely, that the one foloweth the other? as when thou ſeeſt a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant folowyng his maiſter. Although there be a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene their two motions in this reſpecte, that the one, which cometh after, foloweth the other, that goeth before in their owne proper being, Yet ther is no ſuch difference of before and after betwene them, in reſpecte of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in thy ſight, whiche doth receiue, complet, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende them both to gether at once. For therin, they haue nether before nor after, as thei haue in their owne proper beyng. For if thei had, thou ſhuldeſt not ſee them both at once, as thou doſt, but one after an other as they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>If I doe not ſee them as thei are, then my ſight in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is deceiued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No not ſo, for thou ſeeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only as thei are, in reſpecte of theyr being in them ſelfes, but alſo far otherwiſe then ſo, in reſpect of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in thy ſight, for the behauor of their being in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes is one thyng. And the behauor of their being in thy ſight, is an other. And that not onely becauſe the one is as who ſaie naturall &amp; the other accidentall, but alſo becauſe that, whiche is ſucceſſiue and conſequent in the one beyng, is all together very preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the other. For els, thou ſhuldeſt not (as I ſayde) ſee them both at once and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gether: wherfore ſith it may by this apere that the ſight of man is able in ſome kind of thingꝭ, as ſone to reche that, whiche foloweth &amp; cometh after, as that which doth precede &amp; goe before, &amp; to ſee that, euen preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which in it ſelfe is but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent: how muche more is the ſight of all mighty gods
<pb facs="tcp:3752:41"/>
moſte prouident and infinite knowlage, able ſo to do in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kynde of thing, what ſo euer it be? Therfore before hym (as I ſayd) there is no difference betwene the direct deniall goyng before, and the conſequente deniall whith commeth after. But as well the conſequente as the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, are ther become, euen both lyke preſent, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what difference betwene them in that reſpect? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reſteth the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertee, of moſte perfit iudgement.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 35.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then if ther be no difference betwene them, but bothe one before God, it muſt nedes followe, that it ſhulde be as great a faut to denie any parte of the fayth conſequentlie, as it is to denie it directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Haſt thou ſpied that now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue ſpied this, that it foloweth of your ſaying.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I tolde the as much before, if thou hadeſt marked it well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>yet I can not beleue it, for all that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No can?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherfore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe then it were as good for an heretike, to denie all the whole faith directly, as to deny directly but the leaſte parte of it, when therin is denied (by your ſaying) all the reſt conſequentlie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not ſay, it were as good, but I will ſay, it were not ſo euill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>what not ſo euill to denie all the partꝭ of the whole fayth direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it is to deny directly but ſome of them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>So I ſay, although the ſame ſome, were but one of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke ther be very ſmal reaſon therin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſmal ſo euer thou take it, yet ſo great thou ſhalt find it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>That wold I fayne ſee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then ſuppoſe two heretikꝭ, of the which, one denieth all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part of the faith directly and the other derectly but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3752:41"/>
ſome, or one parte therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Contente.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then thou muſt graunt me three thinges, which no man will denie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>what are they?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſt is, that the more euill any man doth, the wors he is. The ſeconde is, that euery mans euel, is other to the hurt of hym ſelfe only, or els to the hurt of hym ſelfe, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo: And the thirde is, that his euell, whiche exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the hurt of other, is wors to him ſelf, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is his euel which extendeth no farder then to the hurt of him ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>To al theſe, I muſte nedes agree.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAT.</speaker>
                  <p>Then there is no doubt, but that heretike, whiche deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but one parte of the faith directly, is a thouſand folde worſe, then the other is, whiche directlie denieth them all together. For howe coulde his euill that denieth them all together directly, hurt any mo but hym ſelfe? In ſo muche that if he woulde, how ſhulde he be hard? I will not ſay or aſke what good man, but what other he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike is there, beſide any one of the ſame ſorte, that wold abide the heryng of hym? yea what good chriſten man, wolde not be moued with a more thankfull mynde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde god, for the gyfte and preſeruacion of his owne fayth, and with a more diligente reſpecte to the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion and keping therof, for that he ſeeth one ſo farre gone, as hath loſte his altogether in euery poynt? ſo that other folke ſhulde by hym, take rather good then hurt. But as touching the other heretike, which denieth direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but parte, looke how muche it is leſſe, that he directly denieth, ſo many mo ther be, that doth not perceue it. And the moe there bee, that doth not perceue it, the moe therewith bee the ſoner deceued. And the moe ther bee, that be therwith the ſooner deceued, tho moe catche hurte &amp; be therwith infected And the mo ther be, that be
<pb facs="tcp:3752:42"/>
therwith infected, the more his euill muſt nedes bee, which is the cauſe of it. And beſide this, how hath any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies ben ſowed, multiplied, and increaced, ſo greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people (as to many hath bene) but by hym, which ſemed to haue ſo muche of the fayth, that he was long thought, to lacke therof nothing at al? But yet he did for all that, As the lamentable euill, that folowed therof, did at length more and more, playnly declare: But by hym which denieth altogether, there coulde neuer any ſuche thing be brought about: for he (as I ſayd) is one, that no man wold here. Beleued therfore how coulde he be? if he coulde not be beleued, no man by him coulde be deceued, if no man by him could be deceued, clere it is that his euill, could hurt no moe but him ſelf, if his euell could hurt no moe but him ſelfe, farre wors is his euill, which hurteth not onely hym ſelfe but alſo many other beſide. And that doeth he, which directly denieth but parte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet he that directly denieth all, and can hurt therfore, no man els, but him ſelfe alone, is yet as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as the other is, to hurt as many as the other doth. Wherfore he muſt be as euill as the other is, becauſe his wilfull intencion therein is no leſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That folowith not, for when that euill intencion, which can not extende to the purpoſe thereof, for lacke of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer or libertee to perfourme it with all, Can not bee ſo euill as that, which hath no reſtraint or lette of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge vnto it, by reaſon wherof, it neuer fayleth to take effect: his euill muſt nedes bee worſe, which is able to extende, bothe to the hurte of him ſelf, and alſo of many other moe, then is his euill, which can extende no fardir, but onely to the hurt of him ſelfe, and of no man els: And therfore becauſe no man wich his owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3752:42"/>
can hurte an other, but that he doth farder hurt hym ſelfe alſo in the ſame. And the euill of him, that denieth but one article or two, hurteth ſome tyme many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes mo: It muſte therefore nedes folowe, that his euill, is euen to hym ſelfe, ſo muche worſe then is his, whiche directly denieth them all, whereby he hurteth no man els but hym ſelf a lone: excepte thou wilte ſaie of euill workers, the more miſchife they do, the leſſe euill it is to them ſelfes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERET.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye maie bee ſure I will not ſaie ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATHO.</speaker>
                  <p>Then eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently by this it maie well appere, that farre wors is he (as I ſayde) both to him ſelfe and alſo to other, whiche denieth but one perte of the faythe directly, then is he that directly denieth Chriſte him ſelfe, and altogether.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 36.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then how may that agree with this, that the oftener Chriſt be denied, the more wickedneſſe (ye know) it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That I graunt: But herein is no ſuch caſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>yes, and that will I proue, for he that denieth any one article of the feith, denieth the trewth therof. And he that denieth the trewthe thereof, denieth the trewth of Chriſt. And he that deniethe the trewth of Chriſt, denieth him. Therfore it muſte nedꝭ folow, that he which direttly denieth the trewth of Chriſt in many articles, denieth Chriſte therein more oftener then doeth he, whiche directly denieth it, but in one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle or in two. Wherfore he that denieth directly moſt articles, muſte nedes be ſo much worſe, then the other is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That foloweth not, for the one denieth not the trewth of Chriſt in ſo many articles directly, but the
<pb facs="tcp:3752:43"/>
other denieth it in as many, conſeqently: And as euill it is to denie it conſequently, as it is to denie it directly, and ſo proued before. Therfore, as euill is he that deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it directly but in one article alone, as is he, whiche denieth it directly in mo, or in all together. And beſide this, I ſai that none of them both, denieth the trewth any more but once. For as he that killeth a man with twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrokes, killeth hym not lykewiſe twentie tymes: but in very dede no more but once: And as muche doth he, that killeth hym at one ſtroke: ſo he that directly denieth the trewthe of chriſte in twentie articles, denieth it not twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tymes becauſe of that: but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very once in dede. And no leſſe doth he, that denieth it directly but in one article alone. For a thyng is not alwaie ſo many diuerſe times denied, as the deniall therof is vocally ſpoken, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly expreſſed: for the voice wherby the deniall is ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed forthe, is not the very deniall it ſelfe, but onely a meane to ſhewe it by. For the deniall it ſelfe, whan the voice is gone and paſte, abideth ſtill within, all one and the very ſame, that it was euen then and alſo before, at the firſte. Therfore when there is none other denied in this article or in that, then there is in any other or in all the reſte, the deniyng of the trewthe in twentie articles, can no more make it twentie times denied, then the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of one ſentence in twentie places, doth make it twentie ſentences. For when the trewthe beynge but one in all articles, is once denied in one article alone, how many ſo euer of them beſide, be denied afterwarde, they make not ſo many denials of the trewthe that is in them, but they make (as it were) ſo many ſhewynges, reherſals, or repetitions of the ſame, and nothyng els. For when the very deniall of a thinge, doth conſiſte in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3752:43"/>
mynde, &amp; not in the voice, whiche is but an inſtrument to expreſſe it with all, &amp; is not in dede (as I ſaide) the deniall it felfe. Clere it is, that the thyng being but one, can neuer be twiſe denied, excepte it be once graunted betwene. For otherwiſe, it is but one continuall, &amp; not diuerſe &amp; ſeuerall, although it be neuer ſo ofte expreſſed, or in ſo many thingꝭ or ſondry waies reherſed. For it is two thynges to ſhew the twentie times or in twenty thyngꝭ, what I denie, &amp; to denie that twentie times, which I ſhew the. Becauſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, ther is twentie denials, &amp; in the other but one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but what ſaie you to this, that moſt men do thinke, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thyng that is denied, to be ſo often denied, as they hyer the deniall therof expreſſed, &amp; repreſented vnto their eares.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is no mattier, for therin conſider not they, whether it do ſtill continew and abide all one, as well whan it is not expreſſed and ſhewed forthe, but kepte before &amp; after within, as whan it is moſt manifeſtly and openly diſcloſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it ſo be. But yet, what ſaith the goſpell?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaieſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>HERE.<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note>
                     </hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mary that Peter denied Chriſte thriſe, whiche is alſo cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this your ſaiyng.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No not a whit. for his deniall was of an other kynde than this is. For of that could neuer folow no Chriſte, as there doth &amp; muſt nedes doe of this: for that was in dede but feigned, reſtyng in wordes onely, and not in mynde: for although it ſemed, &amp; ſo be ſaide (as right well it maie) that he denied Chriſte. Yet maie it be trewly ſome waie ſaide the contrary. For he denied but his owne knowlage of hym, and nothynge els. for it is two thynges for me to denie the, that is to ſaie, to denie what thou art, and to denie that I knowe the. Whiche kynde of deniall, no heretikes doth vſe, that is to wit, to denie that they knowe Chriſte: although
<pb facs="tcp:3752:44"/>
they might well enough, ſith they be of that ſorte, or farre wors,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> then to whom chriſte ſayth, I knowe not you. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, they do not ſo. For all the mainy of them, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to graunt hym, and no men in maner more: but yet for all that, they do in dede, denie, not that thei knowe hym, but that &amp; what he is, which is ten times wors: For ſeint peter denied not what he was, but only that he knew hym. Whiche was but a feigned deniall, and did onely conſiſte in woordes. For it was farre otherwiſe in his mynde, becauſe he did both thinke &amp; know that he knewe him well enough. And did for feare but feigne the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: wherfore all ſuch feigned denials, whiche hath there beyng not in minde but onely in wordes, may trewly be ſaid alwaie to be ſo many, as thei be ſondry times reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But ſo may not this hereticall deniall, that we now ſpeake of. whiche is of an other ſorte, and doth reſt in the minde continually, muche more ſubtilly, muche more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, &amp; therfore a thowſande folde more perilouſly, then is poſſible euen for the inuentours therof them ſelfes, to perceiue or thinke: And therfore all this conſidered, it is not harde for the to ſee, that the trewth beyng once denied in any one article alone, it is not the deniall in many or all the reſt of the articles afterwarde, that can make it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the oftner denied by reaſon of that: when in that one, it ſtandeth ſo full in deniall before, that it can not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied againe, excepte it be one (as I ſayde) graunted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene: wherfore cleane againſt thine opinion, no ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth he denie the trewthe of Chriſte, whiche directly denieth al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> articles one after an other, then doth he which directly denieth but one alone. And what therfore canſt thou fynde els betwene them, but that he is yet as euill as the other, whom thou takeſt to be muche wors.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3752:44"/>
               <head>Cap. 37.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen this I can finde, that a faute can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſo euill, whan it is done vnwares and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, as when it is done, both ware &amp; willyngly. And therfore he that denieth Chriſte but conſequently, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les denieth him vnwares and ignorantly againſt his wil. For with expreſſed wordꝭ, he doth both graunt &amp; confeſſe hym plainly: but he, whiche denieth all tharticles direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (wherin he denieth him alſo with apparte wordes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly) denieth him euen very ware &amp; willyngly, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſte nedes be muche wors, then the other is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but how canſt thou proue, that he whiche denieth all the articles of the faithe directly, doth therin denie Chriſte bothe ware and willyngly, as thou ſaieſt he doth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe ſaie ye that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt harde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede your queſtion therin ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me nowe conſider with my ſelfe, that if I ſhulde take Ipon me to proue it, by his deniall of this article or that, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt to the laſte, ye wold ſay perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that he denieth hym but conſequently, and ſo vnware &amp; ignorantly in any of them all. wherwith I wold holde my ſelfe, if it were not for this article of the Crede. <hi>I beleue in Ieſus Chriſte his onely ſonne.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATHH.</speaker>
                  <p>And thinkeſt thou, that any heretike doth directly denie that article?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>That heretike whiche directly denieth all, muſt nedes therin, directly denie that. &amp; therfore he deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth chriſt both ware &amp; willingly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike: But ther is none ſuch. For he that ſo doth, is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly an heretike, but other a Pagan or Apoſtata, which is farder of, &amp; more ſtrange vnto vs, then an heretike is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Then haue you loſt muche labor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>what haue you done al this while, but gone about
<pb facs="tcp:3752:45"/>
to proue, that he, whiche denieth directlie hut one article of the faith, is wors then that heretike, which directly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth them all together. And now ye ſey there is none ſuch?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>So I ſey, for ſuche an heretike, was and is, but in cace ſuppoſed, wherof, doeſt thou not ſee, what foloweth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen this, that he which directly deuieth but one article of the faith, is farre wors then is a <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Apoſtata.</hi> For when he is wors (as it is proued) then the other is, which directly denieth them all. And none directly denieth them all, but other a pagan or apoſtata, it muſte nedes followe, that he is wors, then any of them both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>I praie you what call ye apoſtata?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>He that hath bene once a chriſten man, and yet hath vtterly forſaken the religion of chriſt ageyn, and is gone clene awaie to the pagans and foloweth them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Trow ye ther be any ſuch?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Ther is no doubt of that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then ye graunt that he, and ſuche as he is, denieth Chriſt with a part wordes directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What els?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then he denieth him euen ware and wittingly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>No trewly, for be thou right well aſſured, ther is no man liuinge that wolde denie Chriſt directly, if he wiſt, and were euen ware therin, what he denieth: For ſo ware is he what Chryſte is, which denieth hym directly, as he is ware, what the whole faith is, which denieth all that directlie. And ſo ware is he, what the whole faith is, which denieth all that directly, as he is ware, what one article of it is, which denieth directly but that alone: and that alone doth he not know, nor ſo muche as beleue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For ſuer it is, that if he dyd, he wolde neuer deny it: no more therfore doth he know or beleue the whole ſaith, nor Chriſt hym ſelf nother, which denieth both him
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3752:45"/>
and it, directly altogether, what warneſſe or wittingnes therfore is there here, more in the one, then in the other? alſo there can no man be an heretike, but becauſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth at the leaſt (as I ſayd) ſome one article of the faith or other. And that wolde he neuer do, but becauſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth vtterly that it is no parte of the fayth at all. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it folowith clerly, that if he knew it were, he wolde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer denie it. Therfore looke what lacke, both of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and alſo of beleue, he hath in one article, whiche di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly denieth but that alone, &amp; euen the very ſame hath he in both, which denieth twaine. And alſo in each of them likewiſe hath he, which denieth three. And ſo forth after the ſame ſorte, from one to an other, vntil it come to him which directly denieth Chriſt and all together. Therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that directly denieth Chriſt &amp; al together, hath no more faith or knowlege of hym or it, then hath he, of that one article, which directlie denieth but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame one alone, what more warely or wittingly doth the one, then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but euen both ignorantly together? And beſyde this, when the greatneſſe of fayth may be ſuch, as is of it ſelfe ſufficient and able to houlde and kepe, who ſo euer haue it, from the denying of Chriſt in euery condition. And when it is ſuer alſo, that the very knowlage of him is therto, much more able then that is. How clerly doth it follow therof, that who ſo euer denieth hym directly, neuer doth it ware and wittingly? wherfore notwithſtanding this, or any thing els, which thou haſte hitherto ſayd to the contrary, I will yet ſay as I ſaide (becauſe the trewth is ſo in dede) that as euell is he, which directly denieth but one article of the faith alone, as is he which directly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth Chriſt him ſelf and all together, as euill I ſay, not in this or that reſpect, but vtterly in euery condicion. And
<pb facs="tcp:3752:46"/>
in diuerſe caces (as I haue declared vnto the) alſo much wors, both toward hym ſelfe and other alſo: This diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens betwene them only except, that the contrary remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the groſſe &amp; ignorant iudgement of the commune ſorte. The cauſe wherof, I tolde the before (as it is in dede) euen to be this, that they are able to ſee and perceue (as they do) the whole euil of the one: and in compariſon therof, obſcurely ſo ſmal a parte of the other, that ſome ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it more, ſome leſſe, ſum very little, &amp; ſum no euil at al.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 38.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, the daie (ye may ſee) is farre ſpente, and I haue yet a mile or twaine to go.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>A, now I perceue thow lackeſt matter, or els thou art we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of ſo muche talke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Our talke hath laſted a great while.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That is long of the, for if thou woldeſt haue bene content with enough, it had ben done, long eare this. But neuertheleſſe, to make an ende with all, Thou ſhalt haue my frendly aduiſe and counſaill, not only wel to remember, what I haue ſaid vnto the, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the miſerable ſtate of this vnfeithfull and peruerſe generation. But alſo farder to conſider of what condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and properte it is of. which (ſo long as it may endure) neuer ſeaſeth, to ſtudy, ſtriue, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; feight agenſt that, which euer dyd, and euer ſhal, geue it the ouerthrow, and preuail ageinſt it,<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to this promiſe of chriſt, <hi>Porte inferi non preualebunt aduerſis eam,</hi> that is to ſay, the gatꝭ of hel, ſhal not preuaile ageinſt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ageinſt what.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CAT.</speaker>
                  <p>Ageinſt the holy catholike church, the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare and ſtabilite of trewth,<note place="margin">1. Timo. 3.</note> as ſaint Paule doth cal it. of the which trewth, it is alſo written, <hi>Super omnia vincit veritas,</hi> Trewth preuaileth aboue al thingꝭ. yet not with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3752:46"/>
ſtanding al the ould experience herof, this peruerſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion, according to ther accuſtomed properte, nothing fearing the loſſe and caſting awey of them ſelues, hath ſturred vp (as all men knowith) ther damnable warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geinſt this pyllare and ſtabilitee of trewth, euen nowe in our tyme ageine, as it hath done oft before, euen to ther own deſtruction. for ſuch doctrine of late thei haue here brought in and taught, as thei neuer were, nor yet are, nor neuer ſhalbe able to defend, by any kind of thing, only ſecular power except, as it hath apered manyfeſtly all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: For, before they gate that of ther ſide, ther was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy ſcripture, nor ould auncient holy fathers, nor yet any ſcholaſticall lerning, that is to ſaie, any dewe and perfit order of reaſon, that could help, or make any thing for them. But of the other ſide, when they came once to power, and might, as they dyd, vſe that as they liſte, they were then ſo ſafe, (ſay al men what they wold) that it was neither holy ſcripture, nor nothinge els, that coulde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile ageinſt them: for what ſo euer argument came in ther handꝭ, they wold be ſuer to make the concluſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of them ſelues, &amp; that ſhuld be, other the porters lodge, the fleete, the marcialcy, the kingꝭ bench, the towre, or at the leaſt, ſuch attendance, as ſhuld make the reſpondent, ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all, and more then he had: ye and ſomtyme, two or three of thoſe concluſions brought in, vpon one argument, and yet not ſo diſpatched nother: And therfore, doth not theſe and ſuch other concluſions, playnly declare the learning of ſuch diſputours, as can none otherwiſe finiſhe their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentꝭ, but after that ſorte? May it not be ſaide, that theſe men be of a monſterous generacion? yes trewely although it were but for one thing (among many) that I do know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What one thing is that?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:47"/>
               <head>Cap. 39.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>It maie well be this, that there is no doute but good thei doe, or els the holy apoſtle wolde not haue ſaide,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Oporte hereſes eſſe,</hi> it is expedient (he ſaith, for hereſies ſo to be. And becauſe hereſies can not be, without heretikes. Therfore as expedient is the one as the other: and that were none of them both, excepte ſome profite riſe therof: wherfore good (I ſaie) they doe, and yet they neuer the better, how ſaieſt thou to that? For in dede, the more good they doe, the leſſe worthy of thanke they are: the leſſe worthy of thanke? Naie the more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of blame, whiche is more ſtrange. And therfore is it not as it were a monſtruous thinge in men to do good, and take no profite therof: ye to do good, and take moſte worthily hurte therof, and be wors then thei were before: In ſuch monſtruous feates, conſiſteth all the policie and cunnyng of this generacion. For they neuer ſpeake more trewly, then when they lie moſte falſely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>How proue you that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſone proued, and we goe but to this, that when they allege the wordes of the holy ſcripture moſte trewly, they doe yet denie the trewe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng therof vtterly. And what is a greatter liyng, then a falſe vnderſtandyng, and miſconſtruyng of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Beſide this, their procedynges renneth directly againſt the dew order of their owne nature. Whiche na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, alwaie beginneth with the fleſhe, and endeth with the ſpirite. for the fleſhe at the firſte, is before the ſpirite. And the ſpirite at the laſte, is after the fleſhe, when they are once parted: But their procedynges contrarie wiſe, begynneth with the ſpirite, and endeth with the fleſſhe, as it doth now moſt plainly appere. For when they firſte brought forth their newelties, which wer ſuch &amp; ſo ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3752:47"/>
as of the moſte parte, coulde not be knowen, where they founde them, or howe they came by them, And vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſte made vnto them therof, thei anſwered alwaie and ſaide, we haue theim of the ſpirite: The ſpirit is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. The ſpirite is with vs, we haue the ſpirite, for why may not we haue the ſpirite, as wel as Peter or Paule? ſith it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Spiritus vbi vult ſpirat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> the ſpirite wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth where he will, &amp; therfore well to conclude, thei had the ſpirite: by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, to ſuch as obiected any thing to the contrary, and could not digeſt their doctrine. Thei alwaies anſwered in corners and ſaide, ye haue not the ſpirite. The ſpirite is not yet come vnto you: but haue a good hope, he will come well enough at lengthe, if ye bee willyng. &amp;c. But nowe wold I faine know, where that ſpirite is become: for, although we harde of hym alwaie to much at the firſt, yet we here nothyng of hym nowe at the laſt: Therfore this muſt nedes be trew, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other clene gone he is in dede, or els ſo ſhamefully turmoyled &amp; ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the fleſh, that he can no longer be iuſtly knowen, or caled by the name of a ſpirite, except he be (as there is no dowte but he is in dede) the very ſame ſpirite, whiche the holy prophet Oſee ſpeketh of, in his forthe chapiter,<note place="margin">Oſee. 4.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>Spiritus fornicacionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, decepit eos,</hi> That is to ſaie, the ſpirite of fornicacions hath deceiued them. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how there is this to be trew, that this is the ſpirit in dede, which thei ſpake of ſo much at the firſt, who hath ſo led the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all this while, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now thei are aſhamed to confeſſe him at the laſt, excepte it be where thei hied him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lacke of their wordes, &amp; confeſſe him openly, with their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt workꝭ. Therfore if any man dout of this trewth, let him but iuſtly waie &amp; conſider the manifeſt voluptuous &amp; fleſhly concluſion of all their procedingꝭ hitherto, &amp; he ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:3752:48"/>
ſee it more plaine, then can be denied. For what hath all their practiſes finally tended vnto, but only to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> luſt of the fleſh, &amp; ſuch other thyngꝭ as maketh for the ſame? among the whiche, although I can fynde no miracles of their doingꝭ, to defende their doctrine with all: yet I can finde ſome great meruails of their doingꝭ, to declare it withal.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 40.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>What be thoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Of diuers &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I will ſhew the ſome, wherof this is one. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their maried prieſtes, diuers there be, which haue lerned ſuch a cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of their ſpirite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei haue taught their yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g maried wiues of .iiii. or .v. yeres olde, to brynge them furthe children, of .xvi. or .xvii. yere olde. Whiche is a meruaile, becauſe it is worthy to be meruailed at, or wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered vpon, thoſe the whether: And beſide this: an other meruaile I take it to be, that thei haue brought many of their children to ſuche a knowlage &amp; vnderſtandyng, that through the helpe of their ſpirite, the doughter may trew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaie to her mother, I haue bene longer a maiden, then ye haue bene a wyfe, by a doſyne yeres: whiche is a meruailous thing alſo, as thou woldſt not faile to ſay thy ſelfe, if thou mighteſt come to the heryng therof. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it not an other meruaile, to ſee what a lacke, that woman hath, of the ſpirite of trewthe in this cace? for if ſhe had hym, ſhe might ſoone anſwere hir doughter, and ſaie, doughter thou art therin not a litle deceiued. For if all the trewth herof, were ſo well known vnto the, as it is to ſome other, thou ſhouldeſt fynde that I am yet hitherto, no very wyfe in dede, although I be thy mother. And therfore thy conpariſon herin can not holde: Nowe conſider with thy ſelfe, whether theſe be ſtrange mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3752:48"/>
or no. Nuertheleſſe, although theſe meruailes and many other lyke, do playnly declare vnto vs, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of generacion this is. Yet we haue a more ſpeciall token and marke to knowe them by, then all this cometh to: And that apointed vnto vs for the ſame purpoſe, by our ſauiour Chriſte hym ſelfe, where he ſaith, <hi>A fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eorum cognoſceris eos,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> by theyr fruites ye ſhall knowe theim.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 41.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay then ſyr if ye go to that, I muſt nedes ſai more then I thought to do. For ye haue here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their frutes alredie, as in dede thei declared yours, from their beginnyng hetherto, alleged the ſame texte to be mente and ſpoken of you, and not of them: who, therwith, ſo peinted your petegrew in dede, that a man might be aſhamed to here it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>ye to here their ſhamefull peintyng of their lacke of charitee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay to here of your frutes, as they declared them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What frutes of ours, did thei declare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Your pompe, pride, ambicion, malice, enuie, cupiditee, glotony, lupurious liuyng, and ſo forth, with many other vices, mo then the time will ſerue mee now to reherſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Why all theſe be but the comune frutes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fraile pronitee. And neuer faileth to be found in ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, amonge all ſortes of men, in euery countrey, where ſo euer are any people at all. And therfore although they leied all theſe frutes to our charges, yet are they no more ours, then thei be theirs. But in dede the trewthe to ſay, when obſtinate errour began to riſe, &amp; ſought about euen for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his own moſt apte &amp; very proper inſtrumentes, he found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dede, euen amonge vs. Where thei had dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:3752:49"/>
farre more depelie, in the planting, graffing, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theryng, of all theſe fruictes, then euer did we. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cauſed them, as his owne, moſte mete ond apte for his purpoſe,<note place="margin">1 Iohn. 2.</note> to depart from vs, according to the wordꝭ of ſaint Iohn, where he ſaieth, <hi>Ex nobis prodierunt, ſed non erant ex nobis, nam ſi fuiſſent ex nobis, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſiſſent vtique nobiſcum,</hi> That is to ſaie, they went out from vs, but they were not of vs, for if they had bene of vs, they ſhulde haue remained verily with vs: Wherfore trew it is, that they went out from vs, and not we from them, with whom we were neuer, for we are now, euen where we were alwaie, and ſo are not they. Therfore ſith it is plaine and manifeſt, that their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from vs, was not of charitee, it muſt nedes be as playne and manifeſte againe, that it was of the contrary, which is none other but euen mere malice in dede. and that was it, that cauſed them, to taunte vs with thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill fructes which are commone, to thintent they might therby, hyde the reſte of their owne, which are to them, euen propre and ſpeciall: for they be not, the commone euill fruictes of men, which our ſauiour Chriſt taught vs to know this ſpeciall generation by: for then we hadde bene therof neuer the nere. becauſe a commune ſigne or token, can geue no certaine or ſpeciall knowlage of any ſingular thing. Wherfore, becauſe this kinde of men, is ſo ſingular, as ther is no moe ſuche, (although to many by that) Chriſt gaue vs therfore, a ſpeciall note and token to know them by, when he ſaieth, ye ſhall know them by their fruictes.<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> That is to ſay, by thoſe fruictes, which are there owne propre vnto them ſelues, and to no men els. For (as who ſaieth) otherwiſe, ye could not diſcerne them from any other fortꝭ of men, where as by thoſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3752:49"/>
fruictes, which I meane, ye ſhal not miſſe to know them in dede.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 42.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>What propre fruictes of their owne haue thei, that no man hath els beſide?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Canſt thou not tell?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>No not yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then will I tell the my ſelfe, although not all, becauſe I can not: nor yet ſo many as I can, becauſe it nedeth not. But neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, ſome of them, becauſe the purpoſe requireth it: And therfore doſt thou not knowe, that thei went alwaie about, to bring vs in to thexperience of this trew ſaying, <hi>Vbi nullus or do, ibi ſempiternus horror</hi>?<note place="margin">Iob. 10.</note> which may this be engliſhed, Where is no order, there is continual feare, trembling, aſtoniſhment, aduerſitee, or thraldome. And therfore what order lefte they (I meane not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane places, but in no leſſe then in the holy houſe of god, wherin order ought to be moſte regarded and moſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly houlden and kept) what order (I ſaie) lefte they therin vnſhaken, or vnouerthrowen al together? And that not onely by them ſelues, of their owne dedꝭ in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but alſo by their deceuable and falſe perſwaſions in all places. For was it not they only, that cried awaie with al the olde auncient cerimonies of the churche? and that ſo longe, vntill they had therin preuailed and brought it to pas? And ſone after, went thei not about to play the ſame parte, with all the holy ſacramentꝭ likewiſe, only two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, ſaieng there was no mo of them ſacramentꝭ in dede, but only two? &amp; yet of thoſe two, they could not abide ſo muche as the trewth, and very right vſe of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>other. Farthermore, who deuiſed the newe alteration of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruiſe, but they? And when they had done it, I praie the what was it? any other or better then ſuche, as
<pb facs="tcp:3752:50"/>
coulde not content them ſelues two yeres together? And therin to ſhow how lothe they were, in any thing to agree with vs, where we had the <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> before the <hi>Creede,</hi> they put the <hi>Creede</hi> before the <hi>Pater noſter</hi>: A worthy occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of ſuch an alteracion. Therfore how newfangled fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes reigneth amonge them, Their handling of their (<hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion table</hi>) doth plainly declare: for how hath that ben toſſed from poſte to pillare, now eaſt, now weaſt, nowe north, now ſouth, now vp, now down, this way and that wai, &amp; ſildome in reſt? In ſo much that in many places, the chauncel could not holde it, but downe it went, into the body of the churche, to drawe ſomewhat nere the doore: where as men ſaie, it had gone out and cleane awaie, if thei had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffered but a little while longer. Wherfore, if newfangled faſſions, be contrary and ageynſt the dew order of any honeſt mannes houſe, as thei be in dede: how much more then, are thei contrary and ageinſt the dew &amp; honorable order, of the holy houſe of god? how be it, by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we maie ſee, what maner of headꝭ theſe be, from whence they come: which ſpareth not in matter &amp; place of ſo great weight, to ſet forth, theſe fruictes of their owne malitious and propre deceit: For to whom maie we trewly aſcribe, the gret ſpoiling and defaſing of our churches, but only to theſe newfangled miniſters, of ſuch fals doctrine, as we ſee plaine, hath brought it to paſſe? for who had ani ſuche maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, as durſt once to venture vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe deniers of truth, &amp; ſuch other as thei deceued? who could haue thought it to be wel done (as I thinke ſome did, or els thei wold not haue done it) but throw the falfe prechinges &amp; other moſte crafty allurementes, of tbis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? who be they, that bareth to Chriſt, ſuch a ſecrete loue, and an inward zeale in their hartes, that thei
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3752:50"/>
can not ſuffre the picture or Image of his bleſſed body, to ſtande in their ſightꝭ? Who be thei, that went downe with the armes of his holy paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in the place therof, vp with the armes of men? who be thei, that put aweie, the holy ſigne of the croſſe, as euill or vnprofitable to looke vpon: And to ſupply the place therof, brought in Lyons, dogges and dragons, as good and more mete for vs to beholde? who be they (I ſay) that are and were, the doers and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all theſe thynges with many other lyke, but only theſe very ſataniſticall teachers through their ſubtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious &amp; moſt falſe perſwaſions?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr that thei did, thei did it by a lawe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>wilt thou tell me that tale? when theſe be neither the makers, nor yet the folowers, but alwaies the chiefe and manifeſt breakers of lawes, ſo farre as in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lieth? For what lawes, ſtatutes, or orders, hath ben made, ſo ſtronge, ſo good, and ſo profitable, for the ſpirituall comune welthe in eſpeciall, as thei haue not broken, and cauſed to be broken, contemned and deſpiſed, ſo far as they might, for feare or ſhame? Therfore tell not me of their obſeruyng of lawes, againſte the whiche, thei haue ben ſo many waies, open perſwaders. In ſo much that I my ſelfe, haue herd ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the pulpit ſay, that thei wold go before the law, &amp; bid the law, come after lyke a daw. And euen ſo thei did in dede: For tel me by what law, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thei down with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roode &amp; the roode loftꝭ to the great defaſyng of churches? By what law, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thei downe with the holy alters of god, to the deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, in that thei had well beleued before? By what lawe wente they downe, with twentie thynges moe, then the tyme wyll nowe ſerue to reherce? Therfore theſe be not thoſe, that wolde folowe the lawes. But they be thoſe, that wolde haue the lawes folowe them. And
<pb facs="tcp:3752:51"/>
then ſhulde they be no lawes at all, but only ſuch, as thei wolde make them ſelues. For this by reaſon thou maieſt well know, that thoſe, whoſe religion conſiſteth in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of trewthe, as the religion of heretikes doth, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer awaie with their lawes, whoſe religion conſiſteth in the profeſſion and graunt of trewth, as ours doth. And therfore, what maner of lawes thoſe wold be, which theſe deniers of trewthe, wolde other make or folowe, if they might haue their wyll, it is not harde to perceiue: But to be ſhorte in this cace, what is amiſſe in all this lande, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon of any innouacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, alteracions, confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or otherwiſe, wherwith the moſte parte of the people are thiefly greued, but that hath riſen &amp; ſo come to paſſe, only by theſe extreme enemies of truth, &amp; their crafty meanes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Crafty meanes? what meanes are they.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Their fals doctrine, falſe teachyng, falſe preachyng, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulacion, fraudulent flatteryng, crafty liyng, feigned holines, promiſe of trewthe and paiment of falſhede, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of peace, and payment of diſcorde, promiſe of truſte and paiment of deceite, pretence of vertue &amp; performans of vice, and ſuche other meanes, as are neuer to ſeke, nor out of vſe, with theſe moſte capitall enemies of trewthe: in ſo muche, that if thou were not a man ſo blinded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection toward them as thou arte, Thou ſhuldeſt clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue &amp; ſee, all theſe meanes with many other lyke, in commune practiſe among them daily: And therfore, is it harde to conſider &amp; vnderſtande, what kynde of fruites they are, whiche are alwai procured by theſe meanes, and many ſuch other as theſe bee? I paſſe ouer their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlyng of the wyls and teſtamentes of men, becauſe I ſee them ſo ſtrangely handle the moſt holy wyll &amp; teſtament of chriſte: for how much of that will, wold thei haue trew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3752:51"/>
performed and kepte? Thei ſaie them ſelfes, no leſſe then all: And yet we maie perceiue, thei mene in effecte, nothynge at all. Neuertheleſſe they wolde haue all thynges referred wholly and onely to that wyll, to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they might then, waie all thynges them ſelfes, euen after their owne wyll. Thinkyng therby, that their yea, and our nay, and our yea, and their nay, ſhuld ſtande to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vpon an euen grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: for although thei be in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber far to many, &amp; yet but few, in compariſon of all other men: Neuertheleſſe in matters of the churche, whiche be not ſmall, but greatteſt of all, looke what all other men wolde, thei will not: what all other commende, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe: what all other diſpraiſe, thei commende: what al other do graunt, thei denie: what all other do loue, they do hate: what all other ſet forwarde, they wolde plucke backewarde: what meane thei by this? May thei not be called a peruerſe generacion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that beareth ſome lies nowe and then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>In dede as thou ſaieſt. one I confeſſe my ſelfe. For where they bee ſayde to leape from hereſie into treaſon, although it were but a ſory leape, yet the reporte therof is not trewe. For they haue not ſo leide hande vpon trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they haue therein lefte their hereſie, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte doth ſownde: But in dede not leauynge the one for the other, they haue ſo wrought them both to gether, that thoſe, whiche neuer tooke in hande, but one of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, can not yet bee compared vnto theym, in any of them bothe: wherfore, they bee vntrewly reported to leape out of hereſie, into treaſon, when they wyll be ſuer to kepe them together, in a truſte that the one ſhall helpe the other: Therfore what wonder is it, although they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt their gouernours here in earthe, when they
<pb facs="tcp:3752:52"/>
be ſuche very rebellions againſt the trewthe of almighty god in heauen?<note place="margin">Iob. 10. Pſall. 21.</note> How haue thei handled the ſemeles gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſte? not caſtynge lottes for the whole, (as his perſecutours did) to ſaue the vnitee therof: But a thouſande folde wors, ſnatchyng at the partes therof, to tere, rent, &amp; diſtroy it all together. For what diſſencion, diuiſion, diſcorde, ſtrife, contencion &amp; diſtraction of vnite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and concorde, they haue made in chriſtes holy churche, all the worlde doth knowe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>I meruaile what is to be founde, amonge them, that ye wyll take in good parte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Truſt me trewly, euen as much, as in them is worthy: whiche (without queſtion) in reſpecte of thende, they applie it vnto, is nothyng at all: For how bitter thei make (or take) the ſwete yoke of chriſte: And how heuy, they make (or take) his light burthen alſo,<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> it doth well appere, not onely by this, that they haue ſo cleane, ſhake them both of, and caſte them away for their owne partes: but alſo by this, that they haue cauſed, ſo many other, to doe the ſame lykewiſe: for are they not, the manifeſte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of chaſtitee? The perſwaders of fleſhly libertee? The breakers of holy vowes? The contemners of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous abſtinence? The crafty ſecret enticers from praier, when they call it but liplabour? For what haue the done, vnder pretence of commune praier, but brought the moſt parte of the people, from their deuoute perticular, and ſpeciall praiers? Alſo what a malicious &amp; ſpitefull parte haue they plaied, with no leſſe than our bleſſed lady mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our ſauiour chriſte, and with his holy apoſtles, martyrs, confeſſors, &amp; all the holy compenie of heuen? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other then done what they can, to bryng them all, euen out of regarde, out of eſtimacion, yea and cleane out of memorie? as it is of the prophet ſayde vnto god:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3752:52"/>
                     <hi>Cogitauerunt aduerſus ſanctos tuos, dixerunt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> 
                     <hi>veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, et diſperdamꝰ eos de gente, &amp; non memoretur no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſrael vltra.</hi> Thei ſtudied (he ſaith) againſt thy ſaintꝭ. They ſaide, come, let vs ridde them awaie from the naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and let not the name of Iſraell, that is to ſaie, the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beholders of god, be had any longer in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr, this was ſpoken of them in thoſe daies, whiche were againſt all thoſe ſaintes, that were then but here in earthe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſaieſt well, and therfore howe much more was it ſpoken, prophetically of theſe in our daies, whiche are againſt all thoſe ſaintes that are nowe in heauen? amonge whom, they ſpare not ſo much, as the moſte dere mother of Chriſte. For why haue they wyped ſo cleane awaie, all theyr names out of the leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie? why haue they done the ſame likewiſe out of the kalender, as in other places beſide, and that very many? Why haue they made awaie, with all their images, out of the churches? And that with more ſpite, then I can expreſſe? And therfore what is the cauſe that theſe hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall teachers hath done all this, but onely, vnder their falfe pretence of auoidynge idolatry, to put bothe them, and their names, euen cleane out of memory? as though it were good and beſte for vs, neuer to haue them in mynde: And ſo in a whyle not to beleue, that euer there were any ſuche. To this, their teachyng and doynge doth vtterly tende. But herein, what dooe they els, but ſhewe theim ſelfes ſo farre exiled out of the number of that holie companie, That, to come therto, they haue no token or lykelihode of any poſſibilitee? Wherfore, ſo muche of their purpoſe, as they haue brought to paſſe all ready, maie put vs, euen cleane out of doubte, what they wolde dooe in
<pb facs="tcp:3752:53"/>
the reſte, if they had tyme and libertee. Any other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou, but ouerthrow all? Therfore to what ſorte of men, may this kinde of fruictes, with many other like, be iuſtly aſcribed, but only to this vnfeithfull generacion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? According to theſe foreſaid wordꝭ of our ſauiour Chriſt, <hi>Ex fructibus eorum cognoſcetes eos,</hi> By their fruictes (he ſaieth) ye ſhall knowe them.<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> For doubtleſſe theſe fruictes, procedeth not of mans commune frailtee, but in very dede, of a diabolicall peruerſitee: for without queſtion theſe men be of that ſorte, of whom ſaint Paule doth ſaie, <hi>Confitentur ſe noſſe deum, factis autem negant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Titu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>cum ſint abominati et increduli,</hi> which maie this be engliſhed, They ſaie, they know god, but in their doynges, they deny him, when they be abominable and vnfeithfull: Therfore ſith it maie alſo now apere, by the teſtimonie of this holy apoſtle, that they be abominable in their workꝭ, and falſe in their faith, what remaineth in them, wherby ſo many (as we ſee) hath bene trained in to their falſe fraternitee,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cori. 11.</note> but onely their craftie, ſubtil, feyned, vnfruictfull, and bare fantaſticall wordes, with out trewth or honeſtee? For there can be no trewth in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feithfulneſſe, nor yet honeſty, in abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the which two termes, that is to ſaie, by vnfaithfulnes &amp; abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the holy apoſtle (as thou ſeeſt) doth here deſcribe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Wherfore, conſider with thy ſelfe, what a lamentable for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, &amp; miſerable chaunce haue thei, which hath &amp; yet doth commit the leading, of no leſſe then their owne ſoules, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a peruers generacion, ſuch a peruers generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaie, as hath diſſented and ſtraied awaie, not onely from the commendable doynges, of all good chriſten people: but alſo from the pure veritee and trewth of Ieſu Chriſt, And hath brought them ſelues, in to ſuche an vnfeithful,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3752:53"/>
and abominable ſtate, as thou maiſte nowe perceue, not only by ſo much as I haue declared vnto the alredy, but alſo, by the manifeſt wordes of tholy apoſtle hym ſelfe, whiche doth ſaie, they are both abominable, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnfeithfull: And therfore, who be they, that yet doeth folow them? any other but ſuch, as therin, are moſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate? and what hath brought them to that infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitee? any thing more, then that lacke of grace,<note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> whiche cauſeth a certayne waie that leadeth to perdiction, to ſeme very ſtreight? More euer what do they finde in thoſe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whiche cauſeth them to be ſuch folowers? any truth of faith, when the apoſtle doth ſay they be vnfeithfull? or any trewth of vertue or honeſtee, when he ſaieth, they be abhominable? Therfore what is there in them, for the which they do ſo folowe them? any thing els, but (as I ſaid) deceuable wordes, a moſt vnworthy cauſe of folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing? And yet they folowe them neuertheleſſe. But why? Trewly there is none other why, but euen their own ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; weiward wilfulnes: which doth alwai her ken &amp; leane to a wrong ſpirite, directly ageinſt the wordꝭ of ſaint Iohn, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 4</note> 
                     <hi>Nolite omni ſpiritui cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, ſed probate ſpiritus ſi ex deo ſint,</hi> do not geue credence (he ſaieth) to euery ſpirite, but proue the ſpirites whether thei be of god, whiche were ſoone proued in thoſe leaders, if theſe wordes of our ſauiour Chriſte, wer well and trewly weid of their folowers, where he ſaieth,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> ye ſhal know them by their fruictes: Wherfore although this were enough to him that had but halfe an eye, to ſee what manner of ſpirite thoſe leaders hath, yet becauſe we maie ſee with our whole eyes, that it ſinketh not, into ſuch mindes as their folowers hath, I wiſhe therfore, that they wolde but well behould, and conſider, this plaine and
<pb facs="tcp:3752:54"/>
manifeſt monition and warninge of ſaint paule, whiche he doth geue in this cace,<note place="margin">Hebre. 13.</note> where he ſeyth, <hi>Doctrinis vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is et peregrinis nolite abduci,</hi> Take hede ye be not led a wey (he ſaieth) with diuerſe and ſtraynge doctrines: Marke, what doctrines he ſpeaketh of, diuerſe and ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge he ſaith. And therfore the diuerſitee and ſtraingenes of their doctrines, conferred and conſidered with this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſaint paule, me thinke ſhuld cauſe them to beware, not only of the oneſide what thei do, but alſo of the other ſide whom thei folow: for firſt ſo ſtrainge ther doctrines are, that thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues can not tel, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thei cam, nor whither thei wil: as it mai wel apere by this, that thei haue ſo often fayled &amp; deceued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, in ther profe ther of: for where at the firſt, thei ſtifli ſaid, that thei came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no les, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, thei are therin founde moſt falſe &amp; obſtinat liers, for the holi ſcriptures maketh clene ageinſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wher, for a farder ſhift, thei ſeid (as ſomtime thei did) that thei came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the olde holy doctors, therin thei lied as faſt agein of the other ſide, for thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers them ſelfes, do teſtify the contrari: and where thei had no farder to runne, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſay, that thei came from the primatiue church, the verie bokꝭ, of moſt godly writers in that holy time yet remaining, doth therin ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uince their falſhed, that of ther lieng thei might be aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med. wherfore yet vnto this day, ſo ſtrange are ther doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines euen to them ſelfes, that thei do not, only not know, from whence thei came, or whither thei will, but alſo that they are not ſo much as willing, to learne it nother: for when ſuch as doth perfitly know it in deede, doth daily tell them the trewth therof, thei will nother beleue them, nor yet ſo much, as quietly here them: Agein of the other ſide, as towching the diuerſitee of their doctrines, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3752:54"/>
we know thei be, that thei differ not only from the doctrine of the holy catholike church, (without the which there is no ſaluation) but alſo thei diffre, and not in a few thingꝭ, euen among them ſelues: as it may moſt plainly apere, by the ſondry and manifolde opinions, that reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth among them: For wher ſo euer, one ſaieth one thing an other an other, as thei do in dede (the greate matter of the moſt holy ſacrament of the alter to witneſſe therof) There muſt nedꝭ be diuerſite of opinions: and wher ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer there is diuerſitee of opinions, (if it be, as this is, in matters of the faith) There muſt nedes be diuerſite of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines: And wher ſo euer ther is diuerſitee of doctrines, there muſte nedes be lacke of trewthe, (of one ſide, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or els of bothe together) And wher ſo euer there is lake of trewth, there the matter muſt nedes be ſtrainge, becauſe without trewth it can not be knowen: Wherfore by this it cummeth clerly to light, that the lacke of trewth is the very cauſe, of the great diuerſite and ſtrangeneſſe of their doctrines: for the helpe wherof, this only moniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of holy ſeint paule, ſeying. Take hede ye be not ledde awaie, with diuerſe and ſtrainge doctrines, wer of it ſelf very ſufficient, wher enough were no leſſe then enough: But wher much more then enough, is nothing at al, what remedie, but pacience and pitee? Therfore what ſhall I ſay of thoſe their folowers, to whom all this will nothing ſerue? any thinge els, but that thei are becum the worthy partakers, of all the propre fructꝭ, that procedeth of the leaders? of the which fruictꝭ, let this very little of a great deale more and wors behinde, be now ſufficiente for this tyme.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3752:55"/>
               <head>Cap. 43.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr wot ye what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>what.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>It chaunceth well that ye haue here vttered all this talke only betwene you &amp; me: for if it had ben in writyng and openly knowne abrode, I dare well ſaie, it wolde haue diſpleaſed a great ſorte?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>For two cauſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What are thoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>One is the hardeneſſe of the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What, whan it is but all in engliſhe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Although it be. Yet many wolde thynke it harde to vnderſtande, for all that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>That wolde none of our engliſh biblers dee, whiche ſticketh at nothynge in the holy ſcripture, wherin is moſt hardeneſſe of all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I am ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they wolde ſticke at this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Than ſhulde they haue but a good occaſion therof, to lerne and ſee, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inete they are, before they coulde well awaie with this, and other lyke, to goe to an other matter, of a thowſande folde more hardenes than this is of, as the holy ſcripture is in dede: wherfore the hardnes of this, coulde miniſter vnto them no cauſe of diſpleaſure at all, but rather the contrary: And therfore what other canſe is there els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Without faile an other, far paſſyng this, and that is not the hardnes, but in dede the very matter it ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What cauleſt thou that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>The deſcripcion of the ſtate of an heretike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>And wold that diſpleaſe ſo great a ſorte, as thou ſpeakeſt of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye without doubte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art therin clene deceiued: and I wyll tell the why. There is no man, that wil be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed or greued, with the trew deſcripcion of an heretik, if he hym ſelfe, be not one of them in dede: wherfore, if it diſpleaſe not an heretike, it can diſplaſe no man: And an heretyke, it can not diſpleaſe nother, as it maie well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3752:55"/>
by this, that he can not beleue or thinke, that he is an heretike. And therfore he can not beleue or thinke, that this deſcripcion toucheth hym, any more than an other man: wherfore he can no more be greued with all, than an other man can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Ough ſyr, neuer thinke ſo, for all they wolde yet coniecture and ſhrewdly ſuſpecte, that ye ment it of them, and of no men els.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What, when thei can not ſo muche as thinke, that it doth any thynge touche them? There were no reaſon in that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr, reaſon or reaſon not, ſo they wolde doe, for all that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>As thou ſaieſt, we haue to muche experience of them already, to loke for any reſon, at their handes nowe: And yet becauſe of thy ſaiynge, I wiſſhe that this matter were in their heryng, to ſee how they wolde take it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>full greuouſly I may ſaie to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, other they wolde kepe their grefe ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or els they wold declare &amp; ſhew it openly: if they wold kepe it ſecretly, it were their owne, and no mens els: If they wold declare it openly, they ſhuld but therin bewrey them ſelfes, and playnly ſhewe what they be: for if thou ſhuldeſt make a trewe generall deſcription of all felons or theues openly, and than, if any one of the audience, ſhould take it greuouſly, woldeſt thou not thinke, that he ſhulde therin, ſhewe hym ſelfe to be other one of ſuche a companie, or els at the leaſte a fauorer of that facultee, whiche in ſome reſpecte is wors then he? And therfore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo lykewiſe it is, in this caſe of heretikes. For if thei wolde nedes herein, with the vtterance of their grefe, ſhewe them ſelfes, what they be: they muſt be content of the other ſide, that men ſhuld take them as thei be. For ſo men muſt nedes doe, without any remedy, becauſe no man can take a thyng otherwiſe, then he doth know it is.
<pb facs="tcp:3752:56"/>
Wherfore nowe to conclude, becauſe there is no diſeaſe of the body (being neuer ſo lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table) that can be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to any mortall diſeaſe of the ſowie. And no mortall diſeaſe of the ſowle, can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to this pernicious plage of hereſie, I do therfore moſt hartely wiſh, that all men wold temper &amp; qualifie, their conſideracions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance therof, with ſuch earneſt pitee, &amp; daily praier, as the miſerable ſtate of this vnfeithfull generacion doth of neceſſitee alwaie require: And therin to deſire, that it may pleaſe almighty god, not only ſo to ſtay thinfection therof, that it ſprede no farder: but alſo, with his great mercy &amp; grace, ſo to viſet the hartes of ſuch as are infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vexed with all, that they leſe not the profite of the time and ſpace, whiche to them he hath lent, therin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, &amp; ſo to returne, to the ſwete pappes, of our moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mother, his holy catholike churche ageine. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with this I bede the now farewell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Syr, ye will not ſerue me ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Where is that, which ye did promiſe, to ſpeake of frith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſaidſt before, the daie was far ſpent. And now it appereth to be much more, for thou ſeeſt it is almoſt night: and therfore we haue now no tyme, to talke of ſo large a matter, as that wold be, if we ſhuld once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HERE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſir, it can not be longe for any faute ye can fynde in him, he beyng ſo honeſt a man, as I beleue he was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CATH.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſo euer he was, in thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, he was &amp; is, in my knowlage, as ſubtill, falſe, and foliſh, as euer was any of his moſte wicked enterprice, that I haue other red or harde of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir in your ſo ſaiyng, ye do kindell my ſtomake, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are ware of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſo euer I doe therin, I ſaie nothyng but trewth, which I am well able to proue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>That profe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3752:56"/>
is it, that I wold here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou knoweſt it can not be now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>when then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>when thou wilt thy ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, that ſhall be euen to morow mornyng by fowre a clocke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſofte and feire, thou art very ſwifte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke it longe, I may tell to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>So it ſemeth by thy haſt. but eight of the clocke is a faire owr.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I not faile, to finde you here then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou ſai the worde, thou ſhalt not only finde me here then, but alſo, that to be trew, which I haue now ſaid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <p>what, that frith was ſubtill, falſe, and foliſhe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye, as euer was any man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, ſubtilte &amp; foliſhnes, can not well ioyne together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet, whether thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or no, he brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo nere together, that in his head, there was nothyng betwene them, but euen onely falſhed, whiche did knit vp the knot, of all his concluſiions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>O ſir I wold it wer mornyng as it is euenyng.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>why so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>It greueth me to breake of, and to leue this matter thus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou knoweſt the mornyng is not longe hence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HE.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſith there is none other remedie, will ye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber your owre ye ſpeake of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>double not therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>Then for my parte, I will not miſſe, I warrant you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>CA.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore, god ſpede the well, for this time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HER.</speaker>
                  <p>And you alſo ſyr.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Fautes eſcaped in the printyng.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lefe.</cell>
                     <cell>Syde.</cell>
                     <cell>Lyne.</cell>
                     <cell>Fautes.</cell>
                     <cell>Corrected.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.5.</cell>
                     <cell>.1.</cell>
                     <cell>.22.</cell>
                     <cell>any denieth</cell>
                     <cell>denieth any</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.12.</cell>
                     <cell>.1.</cell>
                     <cell>.16.</cell>
                     <cell>much darkely</cell>
                     <cell>much more darkely</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.12.</cell>
                     <cell>.2.</cell>
                     <cell>.10.</cell>
                     <cell>what</cell>
                     <cell>when</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.12.</cell>
                     <cell>.2.</cell>
                     <cell>.11.</cell>
                     <cell>he waie, trenth.</cell>
                     <cell>the waie, trewthe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.16.</cell>
                     <cell>.1.</cell>
                     <cell>.11.</cell>
                     <cell>pluralu</cell>
                     <cell>plurall number</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.16.</cell>
                     <cell>.2.</cell>
                     <cell>.8.</cell>
                     <cell>the name</cell>
                     <cell>of the name</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.19.</cell>
                     <cell>.2.</cell>
                     <cell>.22.</cell>
                     <cell>ſaluacton</cell>
                     <cell>ſaluacion</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.23.</cell>
                     <cell>.1.</cell>
                     <cell>.26.</cell>
                     <cell>nor</cell>
                     <cell>not</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.33.</cell>
                     <cell>.1.</cell>
                     <cell>.19.</cell>
                     <cell>the ſame</cell>
                     <cell>this ſame.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>.37.</cell>
                     <cell>.2.</cell>
                     <cell>.7.</cell>
                     <cell>twen</cell>
                     <cell>twentie</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3752:57"/>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LONDON IN FLETESTRETE IN THE HOVS OF THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Berthelet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3752:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
